<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>aadm</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://aadm.github.io/feeds/comment.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://aadm.github.io/</id><updated>2017-07-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>art photographers</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2017-07-05-art-photographers.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-07-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2017-07-05:2017-07-05-art-photographers.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The world of art photography fascinates me. I especially love those who refer to themselves as &amp;#8220;artists&amp;#8221;, their art being typically exemplified by boring, flat, sad photos where the &amp;#8220;artist&amp;#8221; himself is shown with vacuous eyes, half naked, a cigarette maybe, with another sad human or animal being by his side. Or empty landscapes showing detritus and crap with not an ounce of&amp;nbsp;interestingness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find it wildly entertaining and maddening at the same time their ability to write so much and with so many complicated words about the void their art is made&amp;nbsp;of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love even more critics that find meaning in these empty images. It leaves me cold and a bit angry, I admit, that some of these &amp;#8220;artists&amp;#8221; are even able to pay their bills with this shit they (and nobody else) call&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;art&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Consider this japanese &amp;#8220;artist&amp;#8221;, &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/10/09/arts/design/hiroshi-sugimoto-at-the-american-museum-of-natural-history.html"&gt;Hiroshi Sugimoto&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He takes photographs to dioramas in the Natural History museum in New York, and his rationale is that two representations of reality (number 1: the diorama; number 2, the camera) they cancel each other so that the result is a &amp;#8220;true&amp;#8221; image of the past being depicted in the&amp;nbsp;diorama.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Mr. Sugimoto writes in [his&amp;nbsp;website](http://www.sugimotohiroshi.com/diorama.html:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon first arriving in New York in 1974, I did the tourist thing. Eventually I visited the Natural History Museum, where I made a curious discovery: the stuffed animals positioned before painted backdrops looked utterly fake, yet by taking a quick peek with one eye closed [&amp;#8230;] suddenly they looked very&amp;nbsp;real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what he does is basically takes photos of these dioramas like any other guy that visits the museum. Only, he does it better, because due to his artist&amp;#8217;s status, he&amp;#8217;s allowed to take tripod and assistants and all the time he&amp;nbsp;needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read&amp;nbsp;this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So an assistant, Hiroshi Sumiyama, got inside the curtains, dressed head-to-toe in solid black — a cheap Halloween ninja costume that everyone on the team, including Mr. Sugimoto, wore that day to eliminate the possibility of reflection. Holding up a black pole, he energetically waved a placard attached to the top of the pole during the length of the three-and-a-half-minute exposure, to “dodge” down the brightness of the clouds in a way that is usually done in the&amp;nbsp;darkroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, these diorama crap may be just a divertissement, made it on purpose to have guys like me go mental. Let&amp;#8217;s have a look at &lt;a href="http://www.sugimotohiroshi.com/portfolio.html"&gt;his portfolio&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Done?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, this is even worse than the&amp;nbsp;dioramas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how come Mr. Sugimoto can call himself an &amp;#8220;artist&amp;#8221;? Well, that&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;because&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many contemporary photographers, Mr. Sugimoto’s work grapples with questions of perception and photography’s claims to&amp;nbsp;truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretty clear. While I take pictures of things I see in my daily life, of my family or friends sometimes, the artist asks himself deep (and vague) questions about&amp;#8230; perception, right. And the truth. Maybe even politics and religion. Taking photos of fucking&amp;nbsp;dioramas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;related&amp;nbsp;pieces&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.photoshelter.com/2012/10/are-these-photographers-geniuses"&gt;Are these photograhers geniuses?&lt;/a&gt; by Allen&amp;nbsp;Murabayashi.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="comment"></category><category term="photo"></category></entry></feed>