<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>aadm - gear</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://aadm.github.io/feeds/gear.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://aadm.github.io/</id><updated>2018-03-05T22:19:56+01:00</updated><entry><title>best sensor ever</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2018-03-05-best-sensor-ever.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-05T22:19:56+01:00</published><updated>2018-03-05T22:19:56+01:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2018-03-05:/2018-03-05-best-sensor-ever.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s the Nikon D850 I&amp;#8217;m referrring to. But it can also mean the Fuji medium format &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFX&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s sensor, or any of the latest Sony full frame&amp;nbsp;mirrorless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the point is that I played with a couple of raw files from a D850 and the experience left me cold. I distinctly remember when I first saw what my Nikon D600, my first full-frame camera, could do. I was upgrading from a D7000 with smaller &lt;span class="caps"&gt;APS&lt;/span&gt;-C sensor, and the richness and modulability of the files blew me away. How easy it was to extract the colors I wanted from the raw files; the amount of information hidden in the blacks; the endless&amp;nbsp;possibilities!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to the D850. My friend Daniele rented the camera and some of the best lenses available (Sigma primes; the 50mm f/1.4 and the 14mm f/1.8), went for a trip and then sent me a few&amp;nbsp;files.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s the Nikon D850 I&amp;#8217;m referrring to. But it can also mean the Fuji medium format &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFX&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s sensor, or any of the latest Sony full frame&amp;nbsp;mirrorless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the point is that I played with a couple of raw files from a D850 and the experience left me cold. I distinctly remember when I first saw what my Nikon D600, my first full-frame camera, could do. I was upgrading from a D7000 with smaller &lt;span class="caps"&gt;APS&lt;/span&gt;-C sensor, and the richness and modulability of the files blew me away. How easy it was to extract the colors I wanted from the raw files; the amount of information hidden in the blacks; the endless&amp;nbsp;possibilities!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to the D850. My friend Daniele rented the camera and some of the best lenses available (Sigma primes; the 50mm f/1.4 and the 14mm f/1.8), went for a trip and then sent me a few&amp;nbsp;files.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I started to play with these two shots taken in obvious places in California. I wanted to see for myself if I really need a monster 40+ megapixel sensor with huge dynamic range that can see in the dark. I realize that I am not considering other important aspects like build quality, autofocus, lens availability, but bear with me, I really want to concentrate on the sensor itself and what it can do &amp;#8212; because let&amp;#8217;s face it, that&amp;#8217;s the main selling point of all new cameras: the miracles of a new, updated sensor. Incidentally, it seems to me like only micro 4/3 cameras are more relaxed in this approach, focusing less on sensor qualities and more on autofocus, video capabilities, in-body stabilization, tricks like sensor-shift tech to deliver 80 Mp files from a 20 Mp sensor, etc. That is probably due to actual physical limitations of what a smallish sensor could ever achieve (remember that I loved the pre-2014 Olympus and their 16 megapixel&amp;nbsp;sensor).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the original files, no editing save for a 16:9&amp;nbsp;crop:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="http://aadm.github.io/images/Daniele_D850_DSC0159-original.jpg" width="800" height="450"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="http://aadm.github.io/images/Daniele_D850_DSC0036-original.jpg" width="800" height="450"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And these are my processed&amp;nbsp;version:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="http://aadm.github.io/images/Daniele_D850_DSC0159.jpg" width="800" height="450"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="http://aadm.github.io/images/Daniele_D850_DSC0036.jpg" width="800" height="450"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 1:1 zoom on Half&amp;nbsp;Dome:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="http://aadm.github.io/images/Daniele_D850_DSC0036-zoom.jpg" width="800" height="800"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what I normally do with shots like this &amp;#8212; I make them even tighter in terms of dynamic range; a robust S-shaped curve, so that all darker areas go to deep black. I care less about sharpness and noise that what I used to do. I actually welcome noise now that is so organic and less digital. Do I really need a&amp;nbsp;D850?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, the era of being gobsmacked by the qualities of the sensor is truly over. For the kind of photography I pursue; for the kind of processing I&amp;nbsp;do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have never been a patient photographer, never had the time to properly do photography the way it&amp;#8217;s supposed to be done, i.e. a relentless hunt for photo opportunities, the camera always at hand, wandering across temple-cities like New York or London or Paris doing what Doisneau or Maisel would do. Or living the wilderness like Galen Rowell or &lt;span class="caps"&gt;Q.T.&lt;/span&gt; Luong, waking up at ungodly hours to set up tripods or wait for the perfect&amp;nbsp;light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My kind of photography is stolen from my real life, it&amp;#8217;s those little interruptions between commuting to work and playing with my daughter, cooking with my wife and riding bikes with friends, nothing&amp;#8217;s ever planned or thought in&amp;nbsp;advance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However I do think constantly about photography, and I do spend hours cleaning up my database at home and organizing photos and editing the weed for some projects like photobooks or simply blog posts that will probably never see the end but what I need is perhaps a modern camera, fast enough that goes invisible and just does its&amp;nbsp;job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The D850, considering what it does best, considering the price and the size, does not appeal to me anymore. I still have my full frame camera, which I have kept because of a few older lenses that I have and cannot sell. But another camera is my main camera, a smaller one with a smaller sensor. I don&amp;#8217;t feel anymore the attraction of the absolute sensor quality. I will still probably get a D810 when they will be cheap as chips in 5 years time. Because I fancy a robust Nikon professional body to keep forever, close to that other classic that&amp;#8217;s the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FM2&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="photo"></category><category term="gear"></category></entry><entry><title>late review of the fuji x-pro1</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2017-02-02-late-review-of-the-fuji-x-pro1.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2017-02-02:/2017-02-02-late-review-of-the-fuji-x-pro1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I think that camera reviews should be written either within 3 months from initial purchase or after a much longer time, like 5 years maybe. After a few weeks of use, any average photographer would know by heart button locations, quickly change the camera settings, know what&amp;#8217;s the highest &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; and the minimum usable shutter speeds, how the autofocus works and so on. And obviously shot a few hundreds photographs in different locations and&amp;nbsp;situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/31105310746/" title="20161119_AA42097.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5798/31105310746_7ec3c09e65_h.jpg" width="800" height="534"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this initial period, he is either using the camera (and enjoying it) or decided to look elsewhere. And if he continues to use that camera, he starts to find loopholes, alternative ways to go around certain defects, until he no longer remembers what was the problem in the first place &amp;#8212; and the longer way to accomplish a task becomes the&amp;nbsp;norm.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I think that camera reviews should be written either within 3 months from initial purchase or after a much longer time, like 5 years maybe. After a few weeks of use, any average photographer would know by heart button locations, quickly change the camera settings, know what&amp;#8217;s the highest &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; and the minimum usable shutter speeds, how the autofocus works and so on. And obviously shot a few hundreds photographs in different locations and&amp;nbsp;situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/31105310746/" title="20161119_AA42097.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5798/31105310746_7ec3c09e65_h.jpg" width="800" height="534"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this initial period, he is either using the camera (and enjoying it) or decided to look elsewhere. And if he continues to use that camera, he starts to find loopholes, alternative ways to go around certain defects, until he no longer remembers what was the problem in the first place &amp;#8212; and the longer way to accomplish a task becomes the&amp;nbsp;norm.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So this is the moment to write something about the camera; when you&amp;#8217;re still excited by the toy, but you also think about the many things that could be fixed. When you can honestly tell others what works, what doesn&amp;#8217;t, and find an argument to why you see yourself clinging to the toy until the end of&amp;nbsp;times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that is really my plan here, to put down in words&lt;sup id="fnref:not-a-review"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:not-a-review"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; what I think about this Fuji X-Pro1 that I bought second hand a few months ago; an &amp;#8220;old&amp;#8221; camera (I believe it came out almost 5 years ago), that according to the general consensus deserves nothing better than a place in memory&amp;nbsp;lane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--
And the alternative I mentioned before? That is, writing a review after 5 years? Well, it would mean to take out from the closet the old camera that you haven't touched in years but you still remember the emotions and the decisions that led you to put it aside and get the new toy. The very fact that you still have it in the closet though, means that something special was there[^piece-of-crap]. So I could take out my old GF-1 and write about it, but I already did (yet another of my ["late reviews"]({filename}2012-07-31-panasonic-gf1-late-review.md)). Or I could take out of the metaphorical closet a camera which is exacty 5 years old and try to write the perfect review: about a second-hand camera which you only recently acquired so you're still excited about it, but also aware of its collective, internet-averaged opinion.

[^piece-of-crap]: An alternative interpretation is that maybe nobody wanted that old piece of crap anymore.
--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The executive summary it this: I believe this X-Pro1 is a&amp;nbsp;keeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite its younger, shiny brother is already out in the wild, I like this X-Pro1 and I&amp;#8217;d recommend it&lt;sup id="fnref:recommend-to-who"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:recommend-to-who"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  I have been using it almost exclusively for the past few months, and haven&amp;#8217;t really touched my Nikon D600 and my Olympus &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OMD&lt;/span&gt; (despite having only one lens for the Fuji &amp;#8212; the 35mm f/2 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WR&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The&amp;nbsp;reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The body, and how it feels in your hand. Surprisingly solid when you shoot, no fear of blurry pics when using slow-ish shutter speeds (1/50th and below). In fact that was one of the issues I had when leaving the effectiveness of the in-body stabilization of my other little camera (Olympus &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OM&lt;/span&gt;-D). It  means that the camera has good mechanical damping, like the bigger Nikon that I&amp;nbsp;have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The controls: love the old-school dials, really really love them but there&amp;#8217;s something that I don&amp;#8217;t&amp;nbsp;love:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lack of mechanical &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; control (something Fuji fixed in the X-Pro2; I&amp;#8217;m surprised by the many critiques about this implementation, but it&amp;#8217;s obviously people that have never used a real film camera &amp;#8212; does anybody really think that a physical dial is worse than using the Fn plus up/down buttons if it&amp;#8217;s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EVF&lt;/span&gt; or Fn plus rear wheel if it&amp;#8217;s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OVF&lt;/span&gt;?).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;no visual focus acquisition confirmation when using the camera in manual focus mode and using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AE&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AF&lt;/span&gt;-L button to activate focus (the camera beeps, but obviously it will not beep when in silent mode, which is my&amp;nbsp;default).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the focus ring (at least on my 35mm f/2) is way too long, takes thirty or so turns to go from 0 to infinity. And I don&amp;#8217;t like the fact that it&amp;#8217;s a focus-by-wire mechanism, i.e. it&amp;#8217;s just a spinny ring which does not control physically the lens assemblage. Yes it&amp;#8217;s damped to resemble some sort of mechanical resistance, and it is arguably better than the focus ring in the modern Nikon G-series lenses or those of the Olympus 45 mm and 25 mm, but still, how much I&amp;#8217;d love to have something real, that would stop at the minimum focus distance and at infinity like the old-school lenses (incidentally, is there a reason why these new lenses cannot be made with physical hard stops at either end of the focus scale? is there an engineering issue that cannot be solved or the people at Fuji and Nikon are just cheap&amp;nbsp;bastards?).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;JPEG&lt;/span&gt; vs Raw, took me a long time to decide whether to go for the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JPEG&lt;/span&gt; route which so many people swear by on the net, or follow my usual Raw-based workflow. I was not helped by the stupid way Lightroom treat Raw+&lt;span class="caps"&gt;JPEG&lt;/span&gt; pairs (inability to recognize them as such, i.e. copies of the same  photos, so no automatic propagation of metadata and keywords and no possibility to choose which one was the &amp;#8216;final&amp;#8217; version; incidentally, my old favourite application, Apple&amp;#8217;s Aperture, used to deal with these pairs flawlessly). At the end, after comparing JPEGs with Raw files processed using the Adobe-provided profiles, I discovered that the two things were essentially the same (full disclaimer: I didn&amp;#8217;t go into the kind of obsessive analysis that some weirdos do; if the files looked the same at 100% in Lightroom then it&amp;#8217;s good enough proof for me). So normal Raw-workflow for me. But I must admit to have a profile for a quick, intense, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JPEG&lt;/span&gt;-only black and whites which had given me a few good shots (and zero time spent fucking around in Lightroom, big &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLUS&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above discussion on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JPEG&lt;/span&gt; vs Raw also ties in with the use of electronic (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EVF&lt;/span&gt;) vs optical (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OVF&lt;/span&gt;) viewfinder. I admit that the presence of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OVF&lt;/span&gt; was the main reason why I specifically hunted for a used XPro 1 and not an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XE&lt;/span&gt;-2 or an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XT&lt;/span&gt;-1. I thought that shooting in-camera black-and-white only JPEGs was best done via &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EVF&lt;/span&gt;, just to train my eye at looking the world in mono. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OVF&lt;/span&gt; on the other hand was the option to save battery power, not being distracted by the bright or subdued or otherwise different colors (and the occasional &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OVF&lt;/span&gt; lock-up when shooting consecutive frames). Right now I&amp;#8217;m kind in the middle, using the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EVF&lt;/span&gt; gives me an immediate feedback of focus lock when using the camera in my usual way (manual focus mode with focus activation on the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AE&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AF&lt;/span&gt;-L button) plus setting the film profile to Pro-Neg S and lower contrast/color gives me a bland baseline look similar to the unprocessed &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RAW&lt;/span&gt;, but I do use the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OVF&lt;/span&gt; from time to time; in other words, I still can&amp;#8217;t say if my preference goes to a simple &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EVF&lt;/span&gt;-only camera or if this hybrid viewfinder is something to hold on&amp;nbsp;to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know the new Leica M-D, the one with no &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LCD&lt;/span&gt; screen which sells for even more crazy money than the one with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LCD&lt;/span&gt; (among various other things)? Call me crazy but the simplicity of that camera speaks to me in a way that&amp;#8217;s difficult to put it in words. However, I know myself and never check the back screen after taking a shot. Never. I simply prefer to shoot, and maybe &amp;#8220;work the scene&amp;#8221;, change the composition slightly or the aperture. Using the X-Pro1 with the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OVF&lt;/span&gt; and the shot review off it&amp;#8217;s very similar (I would imagine) to the experience of shooting a Leica M-D. You just shoot, then review at home, not bothered by the pretty colors shown in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EVF&lt;/span&gt;. Oh and speaking of Leicas: the other model I&amp;#8217;ve lusted over is the M Monochrom (the original one with the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CCD&lt;/span&gt; sensor); and it&amp;#8217;s also the only Leica I have actually tried. Again beautiful camera which I would buy in a heartbeat if I had that kind of money. But to reiterate the concept: use the Fuji in Monochrome film simulation with contrast jacked up or lowered down to taste, and you probably have 50% of the experience (and by &amp;#8220;experience&amp;#8221; I mean botch the focus the first time, fuck around with the focus ring, etc; it would be 80-90% if the X-Pro1 had no autofocus and was heavier), 90% of the quality (I&amp;#8217;d argue it&amp;#8217;s even more than that, and I&amp;#8217;m talking about this old X-Pro1 not even the new X-Pro2) for a fraction of the price (mine costed 300 euros, can you believe&amp;nbsp;that?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s all folks. To conclude my non-review, here&amp;#8217;s some photos taken with the Fuji, sooner or later (or maybe never) to be updated, changed, modfied, removed depending on my mood. More of them &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/albums/72157672830866364"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/30997946102/" title="20161017_XPR0029.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5348/30997946102_377c6caee3_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/125 sec. at f/2.0, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 1600, 53 mm (XF35mmF2 R &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WR&lt;/span&gt;, X-Pro1).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/31105210086/" title="20161020_XPR0018.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5530/31105210086_70db646e21_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/50 sec. at f/2.0, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 800, 53 mm (XF35mmF2 R &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WR&lt;/span&gt;, X-Pro1).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/31105305766/" title="20161119_XPR0822.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5775/31105305766_e3ff05142e_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/160 sec. at f/2.0, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 1600, 53 mm (XF35mmF2 R &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WR&lt;/span&gt;, X-Pro1).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/31860991373/" title="20161030_XPR0541.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/404/31860991373_4e4eb805ec_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/2500 sec. at f/2.0, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 400, 53 mm (XF35mmF2 R &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WR&lt;/span&gt;, X-Pro1).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/32632803296/" title="20161104_XPR0609.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/425/32632803296_e2bded208e_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/70 sec. at f/2.0, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 1600, 53 mm (XF35mmF2 R &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WR&lt;/span&gt;, X-Pro1).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/31830475484/" title="20161127_XPR0925.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/757/31830475484_69aa817aec_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/1200 sec. at f/4.0, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 200, 53 mm (XF35mmF2 R &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WR&lt;/span&gt;, X-Pro1).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/31830478124/" title="20161127_XPR0930.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/652/31830478124_e07b9cd3af_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/450 sec. at f/4.0, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 200, 53 mm (XF35mmF2 R &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WR&lt;/span&gt;, X-Pro1).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/30334311643/" title="20161106_XPR0688.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5491/30334311643_02a9edc0a2_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/480 sec. at f/2.0, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 1600, 53 mm (XF35mmF2 R &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WR&lt;/span&gt;, X-Pro1).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/32673304665/" title="20161208_XPR1081.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/676/32673304665_09c460072e_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/160 sec. at f/4.0, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 800, 53 mm (XF35mmF2 R &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WR&lt;/span&gt;, X-Pro1).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/31830507544/" title="20161218_XPR1201.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/366/31830507544_3ee163b6b2_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/105 sec. at f/4.0, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 400, 53 mm (XF35mmF2 R &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WR&lt;/span&gt;, X-Pro1).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/32551324421/" title="20161222_XPR1217.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/330/32551324421_b4c15f96c1_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/160 sec. at f/2.8, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 800, 53 mm (XF35mmF2 R &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WR&lt;/span&gt;, X-Pro1).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/32673332305/" title="20161223_XPR1227.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/635/32673332305_e8b454f02c_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/210 sec. at f/8.0, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 200, 53 mm (XF35mmF2 R &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WR&lt;/span&gt;, X-Pro1).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/32294306980/" title="20161226_XPR1353.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/378/32294306980_ab8ce346e8_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/75 sec. at f/2.8, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 1600, 53 mm (XF35mmF2 R &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WR&lt;/span&gt;, X-Pro1).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/32294371770/" title="20161229_XPR1535.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/428/32294371770_63d4d489d6_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/60 sec. at f/1.0, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 1600, 75 mm (50.0 mm, X-Pro1).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/32632980456/" title="20161231_XPR1593.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/583/32632980456_387f28300d_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/150 sec. at f/2.8, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 400, 53 mm (XF35mmF2 R &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WR&lt;/span&gt;, X-Pro1).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/32632982616/" title="20170114_XPR1637.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/581/32632982616_7eb08a9edd_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/70 sec. at f/2.8, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 800, 53 mm (XF35mmF2 R &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WR&lt;/span&gt;, X-Pro1).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/32520695482/" title="20170115_XPR1728.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/682/32520695482_88c9f492b4_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/600 sec. at f/5.6, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 800, 53 mm (XF35mmF2 R &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WR&lt;/span&gt;, X-Pro1).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/32673209745/" title="20161030_XPR0517.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/263/32673209745_ba2aa9b06f_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/120 sec. at f/2.0, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 1600, 53 mm (XF35mmF2 R &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WR&lt;/span&gt;, X-Pro1).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/31861126983/" title="20161227_XPR1469.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/555/31861126983_c212bb3ab5_h.jpg" width="533" height="800"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/1800 sec. at f/3.2, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 200, 53 mm (XF35mmF2 R &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WR&lt;/span&gt;, X-Pro1).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/31830553164/" title="20161227_XPR1481.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/261/31830553164_d91e53b321_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/200 sec. at f/5.6, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 400, 53 mm (XF35mmF2 R &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WR&lt;/span&gt;, X-Pro1).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/32673435785/" title="20170115_XPR1733.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/670/32673435785_6c4c6b755d_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/640 sec. at f/2.0, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 800, 53 mm (XF35mmF2 R &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WR&lt;/span&gt;, X-Pro1).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:not-a-review"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this really a &amp;#8216;proper&amp;#8217; review? Am I a &amp;#8216;proper&amp;#8217; reviewer? Well, I am certainly not a professional photographer nor a internet gear reviewer; the sparseness of my posts, the lack of wedding photos, the total absence of clickbaits or referral links on this site speaks for itself; I mostly write for myself and I have enjoyed in the past few years to write  short notes about cameras that I have purchased and used. I call them &amp;#8220;non-reviews&amp;#8221;, and I&amp;#8217;ve made them public just because I think that other people may benefit from an alternative view at this sort of things, which is &amp;#8212; you don&amp;#8217;t always need the latest gizmo to have fun or make real work. Quite interesting to notice that just in these days a much better writer/photographer than me (quite possibly also a better human being, who knows), &lt;a href="https://visualsciencelab.blogspot.no/2017/02/first-impressions-review-hands-on.html"&gt;wrote about the silliness of camera reviews&lt;/a&gt; written by adolescents after having used a camera for a few days.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:not-a-review" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:recommend-to-who"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But only to a certain kind of photographer, the kind that finds little things to photograph in the corners of the daily life, that embraces the occasional blurry picture, that is not in a rush to take the definitive picture of his life because he knows it&amp;#8217;s a neverending quest.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:recommend-to-who" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="photo"></category><category term="gear"></category></entry><entry><title>fuji-me-too</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2016-10-12-fuji-me-too.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-12T22:36:17+02:00</published><updated>2016-10-12T22:36:17+02:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2016-10-12:/2016-10-12-fuji-me-too.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The long Norwegian September is a period of the year when I&amp;#8217;m still very much in holiday-mode, with my skin still burning from the southern italian sunshine, and at the same time dreading the dark winter ahead. It is a period when my congenital hatred for office life and rituals reach the highest peak; it is a period where all these first-world problems are channeled into the research of a new camera to play with&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My trusted (and hypothetical) readers know that I have a subdued (and long-standing) attraction for Leicas. Prices and other factors have so far kept me from going that crazy route; perhaps one of these factors is Fuji, a historical brand that, a few years ago, pulled out of the blue a series of cameras and tools that rival Leica in terms of pure appeal (and probably destroys it if we consider the price/performance ratio). This is why I bought a second-hand Fuji X-Pro1 with a 35mm f/2 lens (smaller and faster than the iconic 35/1.4). All for the outrageous price of six-hundred euros. Compare to the cost of a brand new X-Pro2 or &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XT&lt;/span&gt;-1 before commenting on the stupidity of buying a 4-years old&amp;nbsp;camera.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The long Norwegian September is a period of the year when I&amp;#8217;m still very much in holiday-mode, with my skin still burning from the southern italian sunshine, and at the same time dreading the dark winter ahead. It is a period when my congenital hatred for office life and rituals reach the highest peak; it is a period where all these first-world problems are channeled into the research of a new camera to play with&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My trusted (and hypothetical) readers know that I have a subdued (and long-standing) attraction for Leicas. Prices and other factors have so far kept me from going that crazy route; perhaps one of these factors is Fuji, a historical brand that, a few years ago, pulled out of the blue a series of cameras and tools that rival Leica in terms of pure appeal (and probably destroys it if we consider the price/performance ratio). This is why I bought a second-hand Fuji X-Pro1 with a 35mm f/2 lens (smaller and faster than the iconic 35/1.4). All for the outrageous price of six-hundred euros. Compare to the cost of a brand new X-Pro2 or &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XT&lt;/span&gt;-1 before commenting on the stupidity of buying a 4-years old&amp;nbsp;camera.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was not an impulse buy however. I have long been an admirer of these new Fuji cameras, essentially for the way they&amp;#8217;re built (solid metal, grippy dials, real aperture rings) more than their supposedly magic qualities of the sensor or the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JPEG&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;presets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, I couldn&amp;#8217;t care less about the sensor performance, and not because I don&amp;#8217;t &lt;em&gt;care&lt;/em&gt; about the raw quality of my photos, but because we have finally reached a point in the evolution of the digital cameras where everything is just good and enough for most of us. Case in point, almost exactly one year ago &lt;a href="http://aadm.github.io/2016-02-02-a-little-camera.html"&gt;I bought a micro 4/3 camera&lt;/a&gt;; this little gem, paired to good quality but cheap prime lenses has consistently given me files that cannot be faulted even compared to the still-awesome full-frame&amp;nbsp;Nikon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why did I get this Fuji? Not for the sensor as I&amp;#8217;ve just said; not for the size either, the X-Pro1 is smaller than my full-frame &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DSLR&lt;/span&gt; but larger than the my micro 4/3 (this is where m4/3 still rule; there are excellent bodies even smaller than my current one, and let&amp;#8217;s not talk about the lenses, which can be so small they almost look&amp;nbsp;fake).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little aside: despite all the non-talk about the equipment that a serious, committed photographer has to do if he wants to be labeled as an &amp;#8220;artist&amp;#8221;&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (which means: he should &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; talk about gear!), I still find this notion very flawed. The passion that men have for tools is not be underestimated; it is true that true geniuses can use lesser instrument and still perform above the average (Keith Jarrett playing a pianola; Valentino Rossi riding a moped; Daido Moriyama shooting with a compact camera), but using better tools (&amp;#8220;better&amp;#8221; in terms of construction; performance; appeareance) is sometimes, and for some people, just a source of pleasure that may bring additional&amp;nbsp;motivation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, that&amp;#8217;s why I got this Fuji. Because I&amp;#8217;m frankly bored of using the plasticky Olympus, the freewheeling dials and the flimsy and disconnected focus rings. I&amp;#8217;m also bored of the beast &amp;#8212; the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DSLR&lt;/span&gt; all built in solid and long-lasting magnesium and tough plastic whatever; the new full frame Nikon 35mm f/1.8 that I recently bought? Wonderful performance but it looks shit. I actually prefer to use the old Nikkor 28mm manual focus even if I botch the focus every other&amp;nbsp;shot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am expecting a little brick that maybe will not be very comfortable to use in my hands and will not be blazingly fast. But I will take pleasure in the all-metal build; in the dials that will allow me to know what status the camera is in without having to look at the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LCD&lt;/span&gt;; in the limitation of using only one lens, which obviously is my most favourite focal length, the&amp;nbsp;50mm-equivalent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am also quite happy to have avoided the perilous descent into the new-gear trap; I mean everybody says great things about the second generation Fuji (X-Pro2 and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XT&lt;/span&gt;-2), and also the late first-generation jem (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;XT&lt;/span&gt;-1) is according to popular myth an exceedingly good camera. But &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DSLR&lt;/span&gt; form factor &amp;#8212; no thanks; price around the 1000 euros mark and above &amp;#8212; no thanks. A camera straight from 2012, when it was sold for 1500 euros, can now be had for a fraction of that price. Let&amp;#8217;s see how it&amp;nbsp;performs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;notes for the&amp;nbsp;nerds&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;#8220;little micro 4/3&amp;#8221; is a first-generation Olympus &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OM&lt;/span&gt;-D &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EM10&lt;/span&gt;. which I&amp;#8217;ve bought before the MkII came out with a substantial discount (350 euros for the body!). The lenses I have are a Panasonic 14mm f/2.5 (average quality, both in terms of build and performance, but tiny!), and the two great Olympus 50mm and 90mm-equivalent, the 25mm f/1.8 and the 45mm&amp;nbsp;f/1.8.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;#8220;full-frame&amp;#8221; Nikon is a D600 which must be the greatest deal ever, it&amp;#8217;s being now given away almost for free on the basis of all the bad publicity it&amp;#8217;s had over the years with the sensor stains etc. It&amp;#8217;s always been a non-issue for me, even though I had the shutter replaced under warranty just to time-proof the machine in case I will ever sell it. However, I cannot see myself get rid of this camera because I have several old manual focus Nikon lenses that are still a joy to&amp;nbsp;use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes I know that just a year ago a bunch of completely different reasons took me to &lt;a href="http://aadm.github.io/2016-02-02-a-little-camera.html"&gt;invest in a whole other system&lt;/a&gt;. So maybe I&amp;#8217;m making stuff up, or maybe this reflects the multitude of thoughts and motivations behind my decisions.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s be clear that the last thing I aspire to is the be labeled as &amp;#8220;artist&amp;#8221;; in fact I despise it and whoever calls himself that. Let others define you, if they have time to indulge in these silly discussions.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="photo"></category><category term="gear"></category></entry><entry><title>a little camera</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2016-02-02-a-little-camera.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-02-02T20:23:26+01:00</published><updated>2016-02-02T20:23:26+01:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2016-02-02:/2016-02-02-a-little-camera.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wanted to get a Leica this time. For&amp;nbsp;real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know Leica: stupidly expensive cameras that are more likely to be kept in a closet or worn like a piece of jewellery than actually used (it wasn&amp;#8217;t like that before, when actual journalists back in the fifties used it as a fast, robust little camera to be used in the&amp;nbsp;field).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, even if now they seem to be more of a fashion statement, I have always liked the impression of solidity, their simplicity, and that funky way of setting the focus&lt;sup id="fnref:real-leica"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:real-leica"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. But I would have never considered one for real if I had not played with the original Monochrom; that really changed something, the simple pleasure of using and holding this rather large, deceiptively simple and &amp;#8220;dense&amp;#8221; camera changed somehow my perception of Leicas. I will be honest and declare it right now that none of this matters when it comes to photography; but I&amp;#8217;m talking about something else here, I&amp;#8217;m talking about very elementary pleasures that are tangentially related to the actual making of photographs; the same pleasure that I get from using bycicles or a Faber-Castell pencil for&amp;nbsp;example.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wanted to get a Leica this time. For&amp;nbsp;real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know Leica: stupidly expensive cameras that are more likely to be kept in a closet or worn like a piece of jewellery than actually used (it wasn&amp;#8217;t like that before, when actual journalists back in the fifties used it as a fast, robust little camera to be used in the&amp;nbsp;field).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, even if now they seem to be more of a fashion statement, I have always liked the impression of solidity, their simplicity, and that funky way of setting the focus&lt;sup id="fnref:real-leica"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:real-leica"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. But I would have never considered one for real if I had not played with the original Monochrom; that really changed something, the simple pleasure of using and holding this rather large, deceiptively simple and &amp;#8220;dense&amp;#8221; camera changed somehow my perception of Leicas. I will be honest and declare it right now that none of this matters when it comes to photography; but I&amp;#8217;m talking about something else here, I&amp;#8217;m talking about very elementary pleasures that are tangentially related to the actual making of photographs; the same pleasure that I get from using bycicles or a Faber-Castell pencil for&amp;nbsp;example.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I went on and looked for older digital models like the M8.2 and the M9, and for cheap lenses that I could afford; however after a cursory search on the internet my excitement quickly faded off and I realized that I&amp;#8217;d better get something&amp;nbsp;else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/24667920971" title="20151011_OMD0322.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1657/24667920971_15e0438a86_h.jpg" width="533" height="800"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought about my D600 which was not going anywhere being so incredibly good at everything: comfortable and fast to use; incredible sensor output even now 3 years down the line &amp;#8212; regardless of all the shit and dust you can collect, it&amp;#8217;s still basically the same heart that powers the now much acclaimed&amp;nbsp;D750.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the D600 was here to stay; what I was missing was probably a smaller camera that I could carry anywhere without second thoughts; a camera that I could throw in the backpack when I go biking somewhere or carry on my daily work commutes, something that I could have always with me to record snapshots&lt;sup id="fnref:snapshots"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:snapshots"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that sometimes change the balance of your&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/24735187396" title="20151012_OMD0332.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1553/24735187396_248d3a2202_h.jpg" width="533" height="800"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And mind you, it&amp;#8217;s not that I am big-heavy-zoom &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DSLR&lt;/span&gt; user; on the contrary, the lenses that I use the most with my D600 are an old 50mm &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AF&lt;/span&gt; f/1.4 and a manual focus 28mm f/2.8. I am used to bring the Nikon with me everywhere but in actual fact, sometimes it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; indeed a bit heavy and cumbersome (I remember hiking with my little daughter in the backpack and the Nikon stuffed between sandwiches and&amp;nbsp;nappies).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yeah, I could do with a small camera. And I still had good memories of &lt;a href="http://aadm.github.io/2012-07-31-panasonic-gf1-late-review.html"&gt;my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, that was lying unused somewhere. There were these small compact cameras with big sensor that were enticing (Nikon Coolpix A and Ricoh &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GR&lt;/span&gt;) but their lenses were fixed 28mm-equivalent and I simply don&amp;#8217;t see that wide; if I only have one lens that&amp;#8217;s gonna be a 50mm or something like&amp;nbsp;that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/24735192056" title="20151013_OMD0350.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1662/24735192056_10b00d9d19_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I did an experiment; revived my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt;, bought a new lens (a 50mm equivalent, obviously &amp;#8212; the Olympus 25mm f/1.8) and used it to document &lt;a href="http://aadm.github.io/pages/northbound.html"&gt;my trip up north&lt;/a&gt; at the end of August last year. And guess what &amp;#8212; I had fun with it, and at the end I got the proper images to tell my story; not particularly rich or detailed but good honest little black and white&amp;nbsp;snapshots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was undeniable proof that I was on the right track; I kept my 25mm and completed the upgrade buying the &amp;#8216;old&amp;#8217; Olympus &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OMD&lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EM10&lt;/span&gt; (its second iteration had just been announced) and the 45mm f/1.8 taking advantage of the end-of-life discounts that Olympus Europe was having over the summer. The crazy thing is that I paid the body only 350 euros. With the same money I could probably have bought a knob of a Leica. And with 2.5 Leica-knobs I now had a tiny system covering all my most used focal lengths (I still had the old Panasonic 14mm &amp;#8212; a 28mm-equivalent &amp;#8212; from my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;days).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/24643653612" title="20151017_OMD0564.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1465/24643653612_613074d553_h.jpg" width="533" height="800"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been using the little &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OMD&lt;/span&gt; quite a lot since I&amp;#8217;m here in Norway. The 16 megapixels sensor may be rather old, and the stabilizer is only 3-way as compared to 5 of the newer Olympus, and the electronic viewfinder is just decent, but good enough to let you take photos. Pricewise the camera is a star and I would recommend it to everyone that knows his way around cameras (beginners should look somewhere else; too many things you can customize in here &amp;#8212; a beginner should be given this camera with most of the litte buttons taped over or glued to the case and at least one knob detached and stored away in a&amp;nbsp;closet).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some blogger I now refrain from quoting once said that we have past reached the point of sufficiency with cameras. My D600 is 3 or 4 years old and its resolution, speed, transparency are so good that nothing could stop me from using it for many more years except lust for a shiny new gadget (or general&amp;nbsp;boredom).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this Olympus is like a little D600&lt;sup id="fnref:sensor"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:sensor"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;; the raw photographs are very malleable, just like the D600 &amp;#8212; well maybe a little less: a little less potential to recover the deep blacks or the highlights, a little less clean at high &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt;, a little less comfortable and secure when holding it with one hand. But you know, &amp;#8220;a little less&amp;#8221; than a D600 it means that it is still astonishingly&amp;nbsp;good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/24667832401/" title="2015-10-0920151009_OMD0083.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1657/24667832401_c9f699d994_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/90 sec. at f/2.0, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 1600, 90 mm (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OLYMPUS&lt;/span&gt; M.45mm F1.8, E-M10).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly it is a big step above the old &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt;. With that camera I could feel the pain whenever the light was not 100-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; conditions. And composing with the rear &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LCD&lt;/span&gt; was at times very irritating. And the stabilization system? I honestly did not think it was that big of a deal &amp;#8212; after all I have been shooting traditional (D)SLRs with no such helps for a long time. But these little cameras are inherently unbalanced due to their low weight so it&amp;#8217;s almost easier to keep steady a largish &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DSLR&lt;/span&gt; body with a normal lens attached than one of them tiny&amp;nbsp;things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The small flaws I have found are probably rather known; like you should know before even approaching one of these mirrorless cameras that they will exhaust the battery pretty quickly. So you have to have extra batteries (but perfectly good chinese knock-offs are available on amazon for two or three chocolate money). And the (lack of) grip compared to a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DSLR&lt;/span&gt; can be unnerving so you gotta use a strap (on my D600 most of the times I don&amp;#8217;t). Actually there is a tiny thumb-rest on the Olympus that it&amp;#8217;s really a brilliant idea and makes it slightly easier to hold (I know for example that users of the much more expensive Fuji X-Pro have to buy a second-party&amp;nbsp;thumb-rest).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/24761438715/" title="2015-10-1620151016_OMD0452.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1701/24761438715_38072a6aff_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;1/500 sec. at f/4.0, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 200, 50 mm (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OLYMPUS&lt;/span&gt; M.25mm F1.8, E-M10).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two of the lenses I have are also very very good; the 25mm and the 45mm. The Panasonic 14mm f/2.5 on the other hand is a piece of shit but it&amp;#8217;s so tiny and cheap that it&amp;#8217;s difficult not to recommend over the more expensive options out there (also remember that I don&amp;#8217;t care too much about wide&amp;nbsp;angles).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is a flaw maybe it&amp;#8217;s this, and it&amp;#8217;s related to something I wrote at the beginning: there&amp;#8217;s too much electronics inside and this somehow bothers me. It bothers me that the shutter sound is too subdued; that there is a constant whirring sound when you switch it on (the stabilization system), and despite being surprisingly well built, it most definitely is not a solid piece of metal like a Leica. It is also a fraction of a second too slow in almost everything (switching from &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EVF&lt;/span&gt; to rear &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LCD&lt;/span&gt;; activating the menus; locking the focus; etc.); nothing truly disturbing and I&amp;#8217;m pretty sure the most expensive siblings (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EM5&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EM1&lt;/span&gt;) would certainly be faster but all of these things they add up and make for a not entirely compelling&amp;nbsp;experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know very well, I&amp;#8217;m making silly comparisons (a 350 euros Olympus compared to a Leica? and what do you mean by &amp;#8220;compelling&amp;#8221; anyway?). All I will say is that (confusingly enough) this is a fantastic little camera, it gives you the possibility to take great photos (which should be all that you need to worry about), but there is something that holds me from declaring it the best camera ever. I hope you weren&amp;#8217;t looking for a list of pros and cons and some &amp;#8220;final words&amp;#8221; on this camera; I think you can find them easily enough on other&amp;nbsp;websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/24133314874" title="20151017_OMD0579.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1575/24133314874_097dda42a3_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/24761481215" title="20151017_OMD0680.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1506/24761481215_1aefcffac5_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/24134519993" title="20151010_OMD0241.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1571/24134519993_8a1a84138b_h.jpg" width="800" height="533"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For some more photos taken with this little camera point your browser to &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/albums/72157664053048131"&gt;this flickr album&lt;/a&gt;. All the photos included here are clickable too and will take you to their own flickr page where you can read geeky stuff like lens, aperture and shutter speeds (but don&amp;#8217;t do that because it&amp;#8217;s not really&amp;nbsp;important).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:real-leica"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously I&amp;#8217;m talking about the range finder Leicas: the various M-something.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:real-leica" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:snapshots"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The approximate translation in italian of snapshots is &amp;#8220;istantanee&amp;#8221;, which means something that occurs at one moment and the next one is gone. Rather appropriate description for most of the photos I take.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:snapshots" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:sensor"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They do share the same father after all; both cameras have Sony sensor and I can see how similar they are when their raw files are subjected to heavy treatment.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:sensor" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="photo"></category><category term="gear"></category></entry><entry><title>black and white</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2015-03-13-black-and-white.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-03-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2015-03-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2015-03-13:/2015-03-13-black-and-white.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have had this Nikon &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FM2&lt;/span&gt; lying around in my house for some time now. It has not seen much action&amp;nbsp;though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, I started taking photos when I was sixteen or seventeen with a Yashica &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FX3&lt;/span&gt;, and I don&amp;#8217;t really have any kind of nostalgia for those times when I had to wait days before realizing I missed a certain shot, or that I focused on that insignificant detail &lt;em&gt;behind&lt;/em&gt; my&amp;nbsp;subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this Nikon is a lovely piece of metal, so I said to myself, let&amp;#8217;s put some film in and give it a go. After a few half-assed attempts using expired film, I loaded a roll of Fuji Acros 100 back in September 2014, shot with it on a couple of occasions, and a couple of weeks ago I finally got it&amp;nbsp;developed.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have had this Nikon &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FM2&lt;/span&gt; lying around in my house for some time now. It has not seen much action&amp;nbsp;though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, I started taking photos when I was sixteen or seventeen with a Yashica &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FX3&lt;/span&gt;, and I don&amp;#8217;t really have any kind of nostalgia for those times when I had to wait days before realizing I missed a certain shot, or that I focused on that insignificant detail &lt;em&gt;behind&lt;/em&gt; my&amp;nbsp;subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this Nikon is a lovely piece of metal, so I said to myself, let&amp;#8217;s put some film in and give it a go. After a few half-assed attempts using expired film, I loaded a roll of Fuji Acros 100 back in September 2014, shot with it on a couple of occasions, and a couple of weeks ago I finally got it&amp;nbsp;developed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And was I surprised to see the results! Was I excited to look at these pictures that I almost forgot having&amp;nbsp;taken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am never going back to film. I am not going to declare that film has some mythical&amp;nbsp;quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let me tell you, I may start bringing this old Nikon along more often from now&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it will be loaded with this Acros 100 black and&amp;nbsp;white.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;family&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/16531503390" title="201409xx_FUJIACROS100_14 by Alessandro Amato, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8577/16531503390_713f0e5f15_c.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;A mother.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/16693069136" title="201409xx_FUJIACROS100_03 by Alessandro Amato, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8580/16693069136_747780c61b_c.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Dylan, days before leaving for &lt;a href="http://www.dylankier.com/blog/faces-trinidad"&gt;South America&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/16511591827" title="201409xx_FUJIACROS100_37 by Alessandro Amato, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8678/16511591827_79b0e9896e_c.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Vale in a box.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;street&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/16531497000" title="201409xx_FUJIACROS100_23 by Alessandro Amato, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8671/16531497000_4ca5855b91_c.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Parma, La Pilotta 1.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/16717644631" title="201409xx_FUJIACROS100_26 by Alessandro Amato, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8572/16717644631_8bdc81f7fa_c.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Parma, cobblestones in piazza Duomo.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/16531490780" title="201409xx_FUJIACROS100_24 by Alessandro Amato, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8599/16531490780_48a3d60df7_c.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Parma, La Pilotta 2.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;outdoor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/16717616531" title="201409xx_FUJIACROS100_31 by Alessandro Amato, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8619/16717616531_734255cf89_c.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Mountain behind a window 1.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/16717824302" title="201409xx_FUJIACROS100_30 by Alessandro Amato, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8566/16717824302_bf4c66aa0e_c.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Mountain behind a window 2.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/16098950093" title="201409xx_FUJIACROS100_29 by Alessandro Amato, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8617/16098950093_d95c7bcce3_c.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Sara.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/16692977766" title="201409xx_FUJIACROS100_33 by Alessandro Amato, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8671/16692977766_2f0f7beec3_c.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Sara and Vale.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><category term="photo"></category><category term="gear"></category></entry><entry><title>panasonic gf1 late review</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2012-07-31-panasonic-gf1-late-review.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-07-31T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2012-07-31T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2012-07-31:/2012-07-31-panasonic-gf1-late-review.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s been quite some time now that I have &lt;a href="{filename}2012-09-21-thoughts-on-d7000.md"&gt;gone back to DSLRs&lt;/a&gt;, but the little Panasonic &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt; is still a constant presence in my backpack. In the meantime, Panasonic has churned out countless other iterations on the same micro four/thirds concept; but to me it has somehow watered down the concept and only the latest one (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GX1&lt;/span&gt;) seems to be the true successor of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;#8217;s only appropriate to post now a few words on my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt;; I know, it is indeed a very late review&lt;sup id="fnref:nota-fuori-tempo"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:nota-fuori-tempo"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but it could be of some interest to cheapskates that are looking for a nice and little second-hand camera (or maybe convince those of you affected by &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GAS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:gas"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:gas"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt; is still &amp;#8220;good&amp;nbsp;enough&amp;#8221;)&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s been quite some time now that I have &lt;a href="{filename}2012-09-21-thoughts-on-d7000.md"&gt;gone back to DSLRs&lt;/a&gt;, but the little Panasonic &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt; is still a constant presence in my backpack. In the meantime, Panasonic has churned out countless other iterations on the same micro four/thirds concept; but to me it has somehow watered down the concept and only the latest one (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GX1&lt;/span&gt;) seems to be the true successor of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;#8217;s only appropriate to post now a few words on my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt;; I know, it is indeed a very late review&lt;sup id="fnref:nota-fuori-tempo"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:nota-fuori-tempo"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but it could be of some interest to cheapskates that are looking for a nice and little second-hand camera (or maybe convince those of you affected by &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GAS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:gas"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:gas"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt; is still &amp;#8220;good&amp;nbsp;enough&amp;#8221;)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/5725746660" title="2011-02-27_1010831.jpg.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5308/5725746660_b027f4978d_b.jpg" width="600" height="800"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Venaria Reale, Torino.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;what I said at the very&amp;nbsp;beginning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is true what everybody said back when the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt; came out; this is indeed a camera that puts the fun back into photography. Small enough to carry it everywhere on my bike rides, squeezed in my backpack between a sandwich, a sweaty t-shirt and a spare tube. And with plenty of photographic power to shame most other&amp;nbsp;DSLRs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In august 2010 I wrote a short post titled &lt;a href="{filename}2010-08-19-my-next-camera.md"&gt;&amp;#8220;my next camera&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;; the month after I happened to be in Livigno and &lt;a href="{filename}2010-09-11-it-was-unintentional.md"&gt;by pure chance I bought the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/5401364927" title="2010-10-17_1000664.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5259/5401364927_7a9ca37738_b.jpg" width="600" height="800"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Denver.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;my&amp;nbsp;lenses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t have an ideal set of lenses; well to be honest I don&amp;#8217;t even have multiple lenses, but just the one little crappy Olympus 17mm f/2.8. It&amp;#8217;s a lens that always come up second when compared to the Panasonic 20mm f/1.7 but it does offer a slightly wider field of view (34mm-equivalent as opposed to the 40mm-equivalent of the Panasonic). The problem is the maximum aperture, only f/2.8; it is this stop and a half that bothers me more than the optical&amp;nbsp;defects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also have an adaptor ring for Nikon lenses and a &lt;a href="http://wanderlustcameras.com/products/pinwide.html"&gt;Pinwide&lt;/a&gt;, which is a plastic cap with a tiny hole in the middle; however both of these things were stolen from my house last January when thieves broke into my house (they also stole my Nikon F70 &amp;#8212; a film &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SLR&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#8212; and more annoyingly a perfectly good Nikon &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AF&lt;/span&gt; 20mm&amp;nbsp;f/2.8).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The adaptor ring allowed me to use two Nikon lenses: an old manual-focus 105mm f/2.8 Micro and a 50mm f/1.8. The 50mm became a very light long-lens (100mm-equivalent) which was easy to use and gave me incredibly good results. The 105mm is too big and heavy for this camera and I was only able to use it effectively when mounted on a&amp;nbsp;tripod.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/7693974058" title="2011-09-11_1050999"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7125/7693974058_2785e710ae_h.jpg" width="600" height="800"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A chamaleon, Madagascar (1/80 sec., aperture not recorded, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; 200, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt; and Nikon 50 f/1.8).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;primes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the shortcomings of the Olympus 17mm f/2.8, this is a lens that shines on the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt; as it makes it even more compact and minimalistic. I don&amp;#8217;t particularly regret zoom lenses since I have always used (D)SLRs with fixed lenses; I still have very fond memories of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AF&lt;/span&gt; 35mm f/2 which I used a lot on my first autofocus film camera (Nikon F70). The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt; with this lens (a 34mm-equivalent) replicates almost perfectly that vision I used to have with my old film&amp;nbsp;camera.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not being very original here but I want to remember why shooting a fixed focal length (a &amp;#8216;prime&amp;#8217;) is so stimulating, fast, instructive and&amp;nbsp;engaging:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt; because you don&amp;#8217;t need to decide which focal length to use before shooting, only shutter speed and&amp;nbsp;aperture;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/5725172693" title="2011-02-27_1010799.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5210/5725172693_dc003e9b98_b.jpg" width="800" height="600"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Venaria Reale, Torino.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;stimulating and instructive&lt;/em&gt; because you need to walk and move around to make the picture you want, therefore fighting the propensity of using the zoom as a substitute for physically changing your position in&amp;nbsp;space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/5401966320" title="2010-10-17_1000673.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5099/5401966320_7becbe82d9_b.jpg" width="800" height="600"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Palo Alto, California.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I just love watching the nerds that go around the world taking photographs with old film cameras and one small normal lens, or this new generation of quirky cameras (Sigma &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DP1&lt;/span&gt;, Fuji X100, and micro four/thirds such my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt; or the Olympus &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EP1&lt;/span&gt;). It may happen in the near future that quirky cameras will rule the world and that will be the moment when I will go back to DSLRs, just because being trendy is not for&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/5791771894" title="2011-05-20_1020498.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3053/5791771894_5b3ce9d73b_b.jpg" width="800" height="600"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;At Beppe&amp;#8217;s wedding, somewhere in Valle d&amp;#8217;Itria (Puglia).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About primes, there is a &lt;a href="http://www.stevehuffphoto.com/2011/05/03/the-fuji-x100-digital-camera-real-world-review-by-steve-huff"&gt;something written by Steve Huff&lt;/a&gt; that I&amp;#8217;d like to&amp;nbsp;quote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s all about simplicity and knowing what to expect from the camera. After a couple of weeks shooting with a camera like the X100/X1 you will start to be able to visualize in your head what your image will look like. You will know what angle to get, where to stand and you will get out of the “Zoom Lens” mindset, which &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IMO&lt;/span&gt;, makes you lazy. Now of course, sports shooters and wildlife guys need powerful zooms (or primes) but for most of us, including the hobbyists, it could be a great experience to just shoot with one lens and one lens only for a&amp;nbsp;while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do it all the time. I could get by day to day with either a 35 or a 50. My favorite lens in the world is the Leica Noctilux, and right behind that the new 35 Summilux &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ASPH&lt;/span&gt;. I have shot with a 35 for months on end, and did the same with a 50. Did my photography suffer because of it? &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NO&lt;/span&gt;, in fact, it had the opposite&amp;nbsp;effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shooting &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ONLY&lt;/span&gt; a 35mm lens for say, 3 months, will open up your mind to other possibilities. You will not just aim, zoom and shoot but you will look around, think and ask yourself how you can get the best shot with what you have. Shooting at 35mm seems natural. You can get great environmental portraits and even normal portraits if you step back a bit. 35mm is great for landscape and urban shots. It kind of sucks you in to the image at times and is not too wide like a 24 or 28 might be, nor is it too constricted like a 50 can be in some&amp;nbsp;situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;shooting a&amp;nbsp;gf1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t really have tips or tricks. I could tell you that I usually use aperture priority, that I always have the camera set at 100 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; and then I raise the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; when I want rather than using auto-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; settings; that I trust the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AF&lt;/span&gt; generally, but not the advanced modes like multi-point &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AF&lt;/span&gt; or face-detection (I use the single central point then I simply focus and recompose). I don&amp;#8217;t care about white balance as I aways shoot &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RAW&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, my ideal camera is something with a hell of a sensor, fast &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AF&lt;/span&gt; but really really simple, matrix and spot exposure, availability of bright prime lenses and some knobs to switch from manual to aperture or shutter priority and to set either of those basic settings. Everything else is a plus that I don&amp;#8217;t really&amp;nbsp;use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having said that, I did experiment for a while with some settings that make heavy use of all the technical gizmos of these modern cameras; I call this mode &lt;em&gt;street-stealth-photography&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSP&lt;/span&gt;) mode. The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AF&lt;/span&gt; is set to face-detection, film mode to B/W Dynamic (contrast +1, sharpness +2, which is a pretty contrasty black and white), auto-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt;. I trust the camera to focus on people&amp;#8217;s faces, I leave auto-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; on limited to only reach 1600 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; (which makes for quite a lot of noise but what I&amp;#8217;m thinking is just snap something and bring it&amp;nbsp;home).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSP&lt;/span&gt; mode helps when I  shoot in difficult conditions, where speed is key and I don&amp;#8217;t have time to choose shutter speed, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; etc; saving also these precooked JPEGs with a rather incisive black and white helps when I want my photographs to be ready as soon as they are offloaded from the camera, skipping the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RAW&lt;/span&gt; import and the inevitable tinkering that&amp;nbsp;follows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/6751767403" title="2011-10-22_1060738"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7035/6751767403_7f48cf8fb1_b.jpg" width="800" height="600"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Phil and Will, Finale Ligure.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;video&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt; makes the creation of small, easy videos a fun activity, and immediacy is the keyword here; the D7000 is more powerful but it requires a lot more effort.
&lt;a href="http://craigmod.com/journal/gf1-fieldtest-video/"&gt;Craig Mod sums it up quite nicely:&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The camera excels at capturing off the cuff snippets of moving-life along your&amp;nbsp;travels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are two examples of little videos that I made with the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt;, the first one shot on the Mont Blanc in September 2010, the second during a snowfall in Oxford, later that&amp;nbsp;year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="390"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/gMBcbsr2u2s'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="390"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/nIkT1ZauZt4'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;something negative for a&amp;nbsp;change&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Positive comments and reviews are listed at the end of this article. But there has been a certain review which was rather full of negative points which left me surprised. Different opinions etc, but here there is a quote from &lt;a href="http://www.sansmirror.com/cameras/a-note-about-camera-reviews/panasonic-camera-reviews/panasonic-gf1-review.html"&gt;Thom Hogan&amp;#8217;s review&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are eleven (!) buttons and one controller on the back of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt; (&amp;#8230;) And the rear dial is (&amp;#8230;) two controllers because it has a “switch” built into the dial. All this extra work really didn’t make the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt; “better” than the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LX3&lt;/span&gt; for controllability. (&amp;#8230;) One thing that’s starting to bug me are the use of dedicated &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WB&lt;/span&gt;, and other buttons (arrayed in a circle and doubling as up/down/left/right buttons) plus the Quick Menu function. The Quick Menu function is good enough that a dedicated button isn’t really saving me much time and&amp;nbsp;effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So even though one of the key selling points of DSLRs is to have lots of buttons and knobs so you don&amp;#8217;t have to use menus (inherently slower), Thom finds that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt; has too many of them. I know what I would rather have these many buttons than a Quick Menu function. At first it may be confusing but if you use one camera you quickly learn to control it (while if you jump from one camera to another like many of these serial reviewers, I can see you could easily forget which is which). Immediacy is the key, especially with this type of&amp;nbsp;camera.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/7693544200" title="2010-12-18_1010333"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7253/7693544200_427c6206b7_h.jpg" width="800" height="600"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Oxford, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;what other people&amp;nbsp;think&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main article I recommend to everybody that would like to not only know the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt; a bit more in detail but also as an example of wonderful mash-up between tech writeup and travelogue is the &lt;a href="http://craigmod.com/journal/gf1-fieldtest/"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF&lt;/span&gt;-1 field test&amp;#8221; by Craig Mod&lt;/a&gt;.  I have found interesting his perspective on &lt;a href="http://craigmod.com/journal/14mm/"&gt;the minuscule Panasonic 14mm&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also wrote something which at the time I judged lyrical and oh-so-powerful, but now it just seems a bit over-the-top; like something written by the guy who has never been to the mountains before and tries to say something new about a condition (climbing, the high mountains) that countless other adventurers have talked about with more knowledge and introspection. However, Mr Mod has definitely some affinity with words, and this rant is probably totally unjustified if he is as sincere as I wish him to be. Enjoy his &lt;a href="http://craigmod.com/journal/annapurna_moonrise/"&gt;Annapurna Moonrise&lt;/a&gt; because it also has some cool night shots made with the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two good pieces also on wired.com: &lt;a href="http://www.wired.com/2010/01/hands-on-with-panasonics-leica-lite-gf1/"&gt;&amp;#8220;Hands on&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt; by Charlie Sorrell and a follow-up by the same author: &lt;a href="http://www.wired.com/2010/02/a-month-with-the-lumix-gf1-and-why-i-no-longer-use-the-nikon-d700/"&gt;&amp;#8220;Why I no longer use the Nikon D700&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally a &lt;a href="http://www.dannychoo.com/post/en/25129/Lumix+GF-1+Review.html"&gt;proper review by Danny Choo&lt;/a&gt; and an interesting &lt;a href="http://reviewers.tumblr.com/post/535639407/GF-1-vs-5dmkii"&gt;comparison with a heavyweight&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:nota-fuori-tempo"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems like I&amp;#8217;m not the only one to write about the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt; in 2012, three years after it first appeared on the market. There is a &lt;a href="http://www.stevehuffphoto.com/2012/04/10/the-panasonic-gf-1-an-old-friend-re-visited-by-colin-steel/"&gt;nice commentary by Colin Steel&lt;/a&gt; which appeared earlier this year on one of those popular blogs.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:nota-fuori-tempo" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:gas"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gear Acquisition Syndrome. Everybody talks &lt;a href="http://erickimphotography.com/blog/2012/03/04/10-tips-on-how-to-cure-yourself-of-gas-gear-acquisition-syndrome"&gt;about it&lt;/a&gt; on the internet: google it up.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:gas" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="photo"></category><category term="gear"></category></entry></feed>