<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>aadm - links</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://aadm.github.io/feeds/links.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://aadm.github.io/</id><updated>2014-06-11T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>couple of things with my name on</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2014-06-11-things-with-my-name-on.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-06-11T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2014-06-11T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2014-06-11:/2014-06-11-things-with-my-name-on.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A brief interlude to note down a couple of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I follow only one podcast, and that’s &lt;a href="http://5by5.tv/otp"&gt;On Taking Pictures&lt;/a&gt;. As the name says, it’s about photography, and in one recent Q&amp;amp;A episode they kindly answered a question I have made; what’s cool however is their …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A brief interlude to note down a couple of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I follow only one podcast, and that’s &lt;a href="http://5by5.tv/otp"&gt;On Taking Pictures&lt;/a&gt;. As the name says, it’s about photography, and in one recent Q&amp;amp;A episode they kindly answered a question I have made; what’s cool however is their comment on my name which I’d like to remember for the future — skip to the 1h18‘28” mark:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="30" scrolling="no" src="http://5by5.tv/audio_embed/?s=otp%2F2014%2Fotp-094.mp3" width="400"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second thing is about Flickr: they have recently published a &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/flickr/galleries/72157645103036432/"&gt;collection of baobab’s photographs&lt;/a&gt; and have included &lt;a href="http://flic.kr/p/dWWjYD"&gt;one of my photos&lt;/a&gt; from my Madagascar honeymoon trip&lt;sup id="fnref:nota-madagascar"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:nota-madagascar"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/8497971885/"&gt;&lt;img class="img-responsive" height="600" src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8243/8497971885_7ee2ba2c16_c.jpg" width="800"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s kinda interesting, especially because I’ve seen with my own eyes how much “likes” (actually, stars in flickr’s lingo) or views (almost two thousand as of today! usually my photos get 30-40 views tops) I have received for this photo in the space of a few hours. Definitely a lesson to be learnt — if you’re chasing the ephemeral glory of internet fame and many likes or stars, better use some marketing skills, post your crap on hundreds of flickr galleries for example, and more generally advertise your work as much as you can. Don’t bother spending your time actually working on your skills, improving your technique or training your eye; on the internet the actual quality of the work comes a distant second.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the picture above is ok but really nothing special, probably a bit too conventional — I’d have preferred flickr to choose one of these two:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/8499270414"&gt;&lt;img class="img-responsive" height="600" src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8087/8499270414_686ebac0ae_c.jpg" width="800"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a 8235="" 8499054624_7a91ae76a6_c.jpg"="" farm9.staticflickr.com="" height="600" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/aadm/8499054624&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=" https:="" width="800"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:nota-madagascar"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See also my three-part series on the photographs I’ve shot in Madagascar: &lt;a href="2013-02-23-madagascar-persone.html"&gt;people&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="2013-02-27-madagascar-luoghi.html"&gt;places&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="2013-03-02-madagascar-natura.html"&gt;nature&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:nota-madagascar" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="photo"></category><category term="links"></category></entry><entry><title>essere giovani</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/essere-giovani-it.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-05-28T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2014-05-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2014-05-28:/essere-giovani-it.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recentemente mi sono imbattuto in due cose meravigliose. La prima, una &lt;a href="http://lightbox.time.com/2013/12/10/muhammed-muheisen-time-picks-the-best-wire-photographer-of-2013/#1"&gt;serie di foto scattate in Pakistan&lt;/a&gt; da un giovane, pluripremiato, fotografo, &lt;a href="http://www.worldpressphoto.org/muhammed-muheisen"&gt;Muhammed Muheisen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La seconda, &lt;a href="http://yaledailynews.com/crosscampus/2012/05/27/keegan-the-opposite-of-loneliness/"&gt;un piccolo saggio&lt;/a&gt; di Marina Keegan, pieno di speranza, gioia di vivere e quel senso di fratellanza e comunità che si ha solo a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recentemente mi sono imbattuto in due cose meravigliose. La prima, una &lt;a href="http://lightbox.time.com/2013/12/10/muhammed-muheisen-time-picks-the-best-wire-photographer-of-2013/#1"&gt;serie di foto scattate in Pakistan&lt;/a&gt; da un giovane, pluripremiato, fotografo, &lt;a href="http://www.worldpressphoto.org/muhammed-muheisen"&gt;Muhammed Muheisen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La seconda, &lt;a href="http://yaledailynews.com/crosscampus/2012/05/27/keegan-the-opposite-of-loneliness/"&gt;un piccolo saggio&lt;/a&gt; di Marina Keegan, pieno di speranza, gioia di vivere e quel senso di fratellanza e comunità che si ha solo a vent’anni.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entrambe le cose hanno un risvolto tragico, scontato nel caso delle fotografie di Muhammed, visto che ci si immagina la probabile fine che potranno fare i ragazzini da lui ritratti, meno scontato ma ugualmente raggelante nel secondo — Marina infatti è poi morta in un incidente stradale cinque giorni dopo il suo graduation day, conferendo una certa potenza a queste sue ultime parole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trovo rinfrescanti le fotografie di Muheisen&lt;/strong&gt;. In mezzo a tutto l’orrore e la disperazione che viene dal Medio Oriente e di cui sembra che l’Occidente ami cibarsi, quasi a scacciare via le brutture della vita (vedi ad esempio le &lt;a href="http://lightbox.time.com/2012/12/20/marco-longari-time-picks-2012s-best-photographer-on-the-wires"&gt;foto dell’italiano Longari&lt;/a&gt;, Muheisen riesce a ritrarre con serenità la naturale bellezza dei bambini pakistani e afghani&lt;sup id="fnref:nota-nerd"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:nota-nerd"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Io ho ritrovato un ovvio richiamo al famoso ritratto di Sharbat Gula di Steve McCurry (la famosa “&lt;a href="http://ngm.nationalgeographic.com/2002/04/afghan-girl/index-text"&gt;Afghan Girl&lt;/a&gt;“), ma apprezzo principalmente il fatto che Muheisen riesca ad affrontare un tema così spinoso come quello dei profughi afghani e i conflitti — implicitamente alla base di storie così tristi — con un occhio ben diverso da quello di Longari e altri che hanno invece puntato i loro obiettivi sul sangue, sulla morte, sui bimbi di 10 mesi ammazzati da bombe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Muheisen insomma mostra quello che gli ottimisti tra noi vedono come la naturale predisposizione dell’umanità, cioè alla sopravvivenza, alla ricerca del gioco e del divertimento nelle situazioni più tristi e scabrose (gli altri, i pessimisti, avranno ovviamente la visione opposta e condivideranno di più le foto di sangue e morti ammazzati che vedono invece come la naturale predisposizione dell’uomo).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sarà un caso che Muheisen ha 31 anni e Longari quasi 50?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;TIME&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href="http://lightbox.time.com/2013/12/10/muhammed-muheisen-time-picks-the-best-wire-photographer-of-2013/"&gt;dice del primo&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Muheisen’s images often capture the innocent cheer and simplicity of his subject’s life, all while managing to evade the countless photographic cliches that such scenes so often present. Born in Jerusalem, Muheisen is no stranger to conflict himself, and his later experiences covering wars in Iraq and Syria have reinforced his commitment to illuminating the lives — and the struggles — of his subjects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“All the children of the world share something in common, wherever they are from,” he says. “An image of boys and girls skipping rope: that could happen anywhere in the world. Children are powerless, and I always do my best to let my image be their voice, and let my picture carry their voice to the outside world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sempre &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TIME&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;a href="http://lightbox.time.com/2012/12/20/marco-longari-time-picks-2012s-best-photographer-on-the-wires/"&gt;nella presentazione di Longari&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 47-year-old Longari recently told &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TIME&lt;/span&gt; that, from his perspective behind the camera, 2012 was “another year of revolutions, protests, violent acts and sheer madness. [It seems] like humanity has lost its bearings, yet again.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was a sad scene,” he told &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TIME&lt;/span&gt;. “All the energy and the expectations of the young people with whom I shared long days and nights in Tahrir Square the year before, all was being hijacked and taken away, lost in political games. It has been difficult to find images that made sense … that were not simple repetitions of what was done a year before.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I was waiting for casualties to arrive at the al-Shifa hospital in Gaza City after an air raid,” he told &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TIME&lt;/span&gt;. “Phone lines with Jerusalem [where his wife and two children live] went dead. It took me some time to compose myself and get back to the routine of doing what I do. But in the faces of the colleagues around me, I recognized what my face must look like every time a bomb or a rocket falls near their families. Photography is compassion — and that scene in Gaza was the most humbling lesson in compassion I’ve experienced in my career.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C’è questa frase che dice Longari&lt;sup id="fnref:nota-longari"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:nota-longari"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, che mi fa pensare. Lui dice che era lì all’ospedale, ad aspettare i feriti. Poi succede qualche altra cosa, e parla di compassione, ma mi sembra rivelatorio il diverso approccio dei due fotografi che si rispecchia chiarissimo nelle fotografie che poi mostrano. Longari è in un’ospedale aspettando di ritrarre scene di feriti e sangue e morti ammazzati. Muheisen è invece tra i vicoli degli slums dei rifugiati, a ritrarre come ragazzini con un passato tremendo, un presente incerto e un futuro ignoto ma probabilmente cortissimo, riescano a giocare, divertirsi, guardare la fotocamera — e quindi noi Occidentali — dritti negli occhi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A che punto si cessa di cercare il buono e il bello nel mondo&lt;/strong&gt; e ci si incaglia sulle brutture e storture della società? Questo me lo chiedo perché io stesso mi accorgo di una mia naturale evoluzione verso un cinismo che non avevo assolutamente a vent’anni. E quando leggo appunto il saggio di Keegan, sono combattuto tra la condivisione di questa gioia che trasmettono le sue parole e un moto di scherno per questa ragazzina che crede che i suoi pari che l’hanno protetta dalla solitudine saranno ancora lì ad accudirla, a spronarla, quando dopo 10 anni ci si ritrova nel mondo reale con bollette da pagare, impegni da rispettare, gli sgambetti, o peggio, l’indifferenza di quelli che chiamavi amici.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non ho risposte a questo, vedo mia figlia crescere e temo un po’ il mio atteggiamento disincantato — ma spero comunque di trasmettere a mia figlia una voglia di vivere, di sperimentare, di abbracciare il mondo intero, ispirata da storie come quelle di Muhammed Muheisen e Marina Keegan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--
** vedi anche: http://www.theweeklings.com/chloe-pantazi/2013/12/27/on-the-blindness-of-warphotography/
 --&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:nota-nerd"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;una nota da nerd che volevo aggiungere sulle foto di Muheisen: mi sembrano incredibilmente moderne e allo stesso tempo desiderose di raggiungere un ideale di classicità che spero mantengano nel tempo. “Moderne” perché sfrutta pesantemetne lo sfocato selettivo in qualsiasi condizioni di luce che evidentemente è conseguenza dell’uso di focali molto luminose e sensori capaci di lavorare ad alti &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; senza degrado della qualità. Mi piacerebbe anche vederle stampate o fare una analisi da pixel-peeper tipo zoom al 100% per studiare micromosso e quanto il piano di fuoco incredibilmetne sottile di un 85/1.2 o 50/1.4 sia centrato sul classico occhio da ritrattista. Sarebbe bello capire anche quanto i moderni fotogiornalisti siano ‘preoccupatì della qualità ultima dei loro scatti se poi la maggior parte delle visioni verranno fatte a scala web, dove il sottocampionamento e riduzione di risoluzione impedisce di apprezzare gli eventuali problemi di mosso, errore di focheggiatura, rumore digitale. Altra cosa che apprezzo tantissimo, visto che ultimamente sentivo fin troppo pressante la spinta dei vari social media verso la santificazione dell’iphone e delle app che imponevano l’uso di pesanti filtri di post-processing, è la scelta di usare colori ‘naturali’ e non troppo forzati. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:nota-nerd" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:nota-longari"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ci tengo a dire che ho preso le foto di Longari come esempio di un certo tipo di fotogiornalismo. Lungi da me l’idea di denigrare in qualche modo l’attività di questo fotogiornalista che ha un coraggio, una capacità tecnica e uno stomaco solo da rispettare. Ho preso Longari come esempio proprio perché trovo che le sue foto siano incredibilmente dure ed efficaci, e se emerge da questo mio commento una certa critica negativa nei suoi confronto è solo dovuta al fatto di non condividere personalmente il suo approccio, ma mi inchino di fronte alla sua maestria. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:nota-longari" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="photo"></category><category term="notes"></category><category term="links"></category></entry><entry><title>hernandez on mobile photography tools</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2014-01-19-hernandez-on-mobile-photography.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2014-01-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2014-01-19:/2014-01-19-hernandez-on-mobile-photography.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://kocistudios.com/about-koci/"&gt;Richard Koci Hernandez&lt;/a&gt; made this video asking if “mobile photography has made us more reliant on tools than on our eyes”:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe frameborder="0" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/4AkDBFsQZ7U" width="560"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; find smart youtube comments. For example this guy wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hernandez makes a valid point - the image shouldn’t be defined by the camera﻿ it’s captured …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://kocistudios.com/about-koci/"&gt;Richard Koci Hernandez&lt;/a&gt; made this video asking if “mobile photography has made us more reliant on tools than on our eyes”:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe frameborder="0" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/4AkDBFsQZ7U" width="560"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; find smart youtube comments. For example this guy wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hernandez makes a valid point - the image shouldn’t be defined by the camera﻿ it’s captured with. It’s a shame he had to spend five minutes saying what he could easily have said in five seconds. I turned off after that - couldn’t take the pretentiousness of his language any more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I agree with this comment more than I agree with Hernandez. He created a cool video (was it all his merit though? I see a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CNN&lt;/span&gt; logo on the corner, and no credits for music, editing etc.), he said some interesting things but it was all ruined by his boring and pompous delivery. I also wanted the video to be at least six minutes shorter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have something against these video “essays”; they are very effective and I appreciate the clever editing that makes this jumble of words and illustrations and short clips flow like if it somehow makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But to me, it doesn’t. There is not much logical connection between a thought and the next.  If this was a written piece I am pretty sure it couldn’t stand on its feet. I had the impression of listening to fake poetry, where words are put one after the other just because they sound good..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, what do I know, I have never been able to understand poetry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;sidenotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having said that, I should really go back and check some of the work that Koci Hernandez has put online. He’s incredibily productive, he’s frickin’ famous too (Emmy award winning, Pulitzer Prize nominee, assistant professor at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UC&lt;/span&gt; Berkeley), and I hate to admit that I like some of his work (but he’s definetely too frickin’ successfull for my taste).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are a few places that I need to (re)visit soon — and which I’d recommend to visit if you’re intrigued with the guy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://edition.cnn.com/2012/10/14/opinion/hernandez-mobile-photography"&gt;http://edition.cnn.com/2012/10/14/opinion/hernandez-mobile-photography&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/koci"&gt;http://www.flickr.com/photos/koci&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://multimediashooter.com"&gt;http://multimediashooter.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://lens.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/06/09/a-distinctive-voice-on-instagram"&gt;http://lens.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/06/09/a-distinctive-voice-on-instagram&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://kocistudios.com"&gt;http://kocistudios.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="links"></category><category term="photo"></category><category term="notes"></category><category term="video"></category></entry><entry><title>networked photography</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2014-01-15-networked-photography.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2014-01-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2014-01-15:/2014-01-15-networked-photography.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have always liked Craig Mod, since I read years ago his &lt;a href="http://craigmod.com/journal/gf1-fieldtest/"&gt;travelogue/review of the Panasonic &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He traveled to Himalaya, captured some great shot with this little camera, and wrote extensive and very well written thoughts about ‘gear’ — linking tech talk to excellent photography and interesting, deep commentary …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have always liked Craig Mod, since I read years ago his &lt;a href="http://craigmod.com/journal/gf1-fieldtest/"&gt;travelogue/review of the Panasonic &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He traveled to Himalaya, captured some great shot with this little camera, and wrote extensive and very well written thoughts about ‘gear’ — linking tech talk to excellent photography and interesting, deep commentary about how it feels to use a camera to capture your emotions. So far, this has been the best review of a camera that I’ve ever read. And it has been that review that inspired me to abandon (although only temporarily) DSLRs and got myself that little micro 4/3 jewel that was the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:nota-gf1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:nota-gf1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- He moved on to become something like a celebrity in the accultured borough of the web; he is an opinion maker now, and he's reached that higher level where he does not discuss common things anymore or stimulate my lowly interests, and what he does (seems to me at least) is pontificating on various subjects. And I have began to dislike his pieces, because they sound pompous and self-important.
 --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However in recent times he has become something like a small internet celebrity and he is very active in discussing stuff like the future of publishing and all sort of nerdy-techie-creative endeavors that appeal to the smart kids of the interweb. He has reached that higher level where the most appropriate way of expressing himself is to pontificate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He’s recently written a piece on photography (on the New Yorker!) that has been &lt;a href="http://daringfireball.net/linked/2014/01/11/mod-cameras"&gt;reblogged by all technophiles and other internet hotshots like John Gruber&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/elements/2013/12/goodbye-cameras.html"&gt;http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/elements/2013/12/goodbye-cameras.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go and read the piece. It is a very good read, there’s a bit of history of photographic equipment that people my age can easily relate to, but the conclusions he reaches do not resonate with me — at all!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You tell me if the power of photography can really be reduced and diminished by the lack of diffusion on social networks; you tell me if photographs and photography are really improved somehow by the fact that you share them with other people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photography to me is such an individual pursuit that the fact that other people may or may not like what you make is largely irrelevant; what’s particularly fascinating to me (bear with me for a second, ‘cause I’m going on a tangent here) is that photography allows people that have no physical talents — like the ability to draw and paint for example — to express their creativity. Nothing to do with peer’s appreciation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this seems to be his main point, together with his belief that somehow photographs will evolve to incorporate other pieces of information like &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt; coordinates and weather (?):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the same way that the transition from film to digital is now taken for granted, the shift from cameras to networked devices with lenses should be obvious. While we’ve long obsessed over the size of the film and image sensors, today we mainly view photos on networked screens—often tiny ones, regardless of how the image was captured—and networked photography provides access to forms of data that go beyond pixels. This information, like location, weather, or even radiation levels, can transform an otherwise innocuous photo of an empty field near Fukushima into an entirely different object. If you begin considering emerging self-metrics that measure, for example, your routes through cities, fitness level, social status, and state of mind (think Foursquare, Nike+, Facebook, and Twitter), you realize that there is a compelling universe of information waiting to be pinned to the back of each image. Once you start thinking of a photograph in those holistic terms, the data quality of stand-alone cameras, no matter how vast their bounty of pixels, seems strangely impoverished. They no longer capture the whole picture.
[…]
Today, it turns out, it’s whatever can’t be networked that becomes less important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So photographs without latitude and longitude or “radiation levels” will be meaningless? I  agree that &lt;em&gt;documentary&lt;/em&gt; photography could be affected by this; but when I say ‘documentary photography’ I certainly don’t mean  photos taken by war photographers but the sterile images that you take of your car after a crash to get the insurance money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--
A parte che uno che non vede la differenza tra le foto scattate con un iphone e quelle fatte con una macchina seria, mi fa dubitare sulle sue capacita' di giudizio; cioe' chiaro che se te le guardi su un telefonino lo so benissimo che e' difficile apprezzare le qualita' di una foto scattate con una D800, ma e' lo schermo del telefonino il mezzo principale per gustarsi certe cose? Non credo che un regista tipo Scorsese o Coppola facciano i loro film con l'idea che poi questi film vengano visti sugli schermini da 5".
 --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then he talks about this hike:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the great joys of that walk was the ability to immediately share with family and friends the images as they were captured in the mountains […]
I saw more and shot more, and returned from the forest with a record of both the small details—light and texture and snippets of life—and the conversations that floated around them on my social networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you really go on a 6-days hike constantly texting and messaging and facebooking with other people instead of concentrating on the here and now? Are you really saying that in order to find satisfaction and pleasure you need to pull other people in the whatever you’re doing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh man I couldn’t find a more depressing thought this grey monday morning. When I’m in the mountains for any of the things I like to do like hiking or cycling or simply making photographs I enjoy the moments, and more often than not, I take a pause and breathe in the fresh air and pause to look at the distant urban lights and just absorb all the smell and the sounds of the woods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharing that moment with your “network” of people, how and why the fuck would you do that? With an iPhone photograph? And why exactly you want to do that, to generate meaningless exchanges of “cool”, “beautiful shot”, “wish I were here”?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that today, “thanks” to mobile computing, we have a serious problem of staying focused while we work, play, eat, talk:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;we walk and run with stupid white earphones plugged into earphones, so we are not aware of the small rabbit that just happened to zip past by us;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;we drive our cars constantly talking over the phone or texting or checking our facebook status, without being aware of the danger we put ourselves into — or that damn biker that is fighting for survival in the traffic;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;we study while listening to music.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we finally switch off all technology and go for a hike in the mountains, do we really need to take a stupid snapshot of some woods and broadcast to a bunch of random people? Why can’t we stay with our thoughts, or even better, walk with no thoughts at all, just relax, take it all in, focus on the physical activity and let everything else fade out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, he also mentions editing (as in processing and modification of an image, not in the purest, photographically speaking, sense of selecting your best shot):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve come to love using the smartphone as an editing surface; touch is perfect for photo manipulation. There’s a tactility that is lost when you edit with a mouse on a desktop computer. Perhaps touch feels natural because it’s a return to the chemical-filled days of manually poking and massaging liquid and paper to form an image I had seen in my head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would argue that if you prefer to manipulate your photos on a small screen you’re not really that interested in the quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For other interesting reactions to this piece, go to &lt;a href="http://theonlinephotographer.typepad.com/the_online_photographer/2014/01/connectedness.html"&gt;the Online Photographer and read the comments to “Connectedness”&lt;/a&gt;. The comments here are high quality stuff, written by people that do actually have something to say and not the brainless morons that post comments on youtube.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:nota-gf1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I posted my first idea on the appeal of a smaller camera in &lt;a href="http://aadm.github.io/2010-08-19-my-next-camera.html"&gt;“my next camera”&lt;/a&gt;, then shortly after I &lt;a href="http://aadm.github.io/2010-09-11-it-was-unintentional.html"&gt;bought my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Two years later, after moving back to DSLRs, I posted &lt;a href="http://aadm.github.io/2012-07-31-panasonic-gf1-late-review.html"&gt;a sort of review of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GF1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:nota-gf1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="photo"></category><category term="notes"></category><category term="links"></category></entry><entry><title>oltre kickstarter</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2013-01-22-oltre-kickstarter.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-01-22T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-01-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2013-01-22:/2013-01-22-oltre-kickstarter.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Quando diventi grande e hai la famiglia, il lavoro… le biciclette e la fotografia e l’hackintosh e i fumetti da leggere… perdi colpi, non sei più al corrente delle novità che ci sono su internet, e ti riduci a credere che kickstarter sia l’unico sito di finanziamento popolare …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Quando diventi grande e hai la famiglia, il lavoro… le biciclette e la fotografia e l’hackintosh e i fumetti da leggere… perdi colpi, non sei più al corrente delle novità che ci sono su internet, e ti riduci a credere che kickstarter sia l’unico sito di finanziamento popolare&lt;sup id="fnref:nota-crowdfunding"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:nota-crowdfunding"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E invece no! ce ne sono altri, addirittura italiani come &lt;a href="http://www.produzionidalbasso.com"&gt;produzionidalbasso.com&lt;/a&gt;; di negativo mi sembra che abbia ha un look un po’ poco accattivante e manca di quei progetti da geek che ritrovi su kickstarter — che sicuramente la dicono lunga sull’inventiva e la capacità imprenditoriale dei giovani americani.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alcune gemme si trovano comunque, solitamente in campo artistico dove per fortuna c’è spazio per sognare. Questo ad esempio è un progetto fotografico che mi piace molto: &lt;a href="http://www.produzionidalbasso.com/pdb_1801.html"&gt;Pig Iron&lt;/a&gt;, con foto che raccontano la eterna storia di poveracci sfruttati dai potenti (nello specifico, i poveracci sono brasiliani e i potenti sono quelli della Vale, una multinazionale che tra le altre cose fa estrazione mineraria).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ammetto che sono sempre riluttante a lasciarmi trasportare dai paladini della giustizia, forse anche per non fare l’ipocrita visto che il mio stipendio mi arriva da una azienda di “potenti”. Sopratutto, ho l’impressione che il senso civico che sta alla base di certe produzioni artistiche sia più forte della tecnica e dell’intensità narratoria. Ma in questo caso fortunatamente il fotografo fa fotografie, e per giunta bellissime, e se si può anche dare un mano anche piccolina a risolvere una delle tante ingiustizie che ci stanno al mondo, tanto di guadagnato. Consiglio anche il sito ufficiale: &lt;a href="http://www.pigiron.it/"&gt;Pig Iron&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Altri siti di cui mi appunto qui gli indirizzi come mio promemoria: &lt;a href="http://www.ulule.com/"&gt;ulule&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.kapipal.com"&gt;kapipal&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.indiegogo.com/"&gt;indiegogo&lt;/a&gt; (e qui ci sono dei progetti tipicamente da nerd come questo dei &lt;a href="http://www.indiegogo.com/Pub"&gt;Pub Pedals&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:nota-crowdfunding"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;crowd funding&lt;/em&gt;? penso che in italiano si possa rendere con &lt;em&gt;finanziamento popolare&lt;/em&gt; così anche se diventa pericolosamente vicino al frasario politichese. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:nota-crowdfunding" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="photo"></category><category term="misc"></category><category term="links"></category></entry><entry><title>direttamente dal cassetto</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2013-01-21-direttamente-dal-cassetto.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-01-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-01-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2013-01-21:/2013-01-21-direttamente-dal-cassetto.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Attenzione, arriva una serie di appunti che butto lì, tanto per levarli dall’eterno stato di &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DRAFT&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Il primo ad esempio lo scrivevo a febbraio 2012 (rileggendolo, lo trovo ancora attuale):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;situazione della città di milano addì 14 febbraio 2012&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;il portafoglio dei possessori di porsche carrera 4 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTS&lt;/span&gt; e …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Attenzione, arriva una serie di appunti che butto lì, tanto per levarli dall’eterno stato di &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DRAFT&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Il primo ad esempio lo scrivevo a febbraio 2012 (rileggendolo, lo trovo ancora attuale):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;situazione della città di milano addì 14 febbraio 2012&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;il portafoglio dei possessori di porsche carrera 4 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTS&lt;/span&gt; e Cayenne è sempre ricolmo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;diffidate delle buone intenzioni diffuse sui blog di quegli &lt;a href="http://www.californiabakery.it/"&gt;esercizi commerciali&lt;/a&gt; che fanno i salutisti, i naturisti, gli ecologisti; dicono che ti offrono il caffè o il muffin se vai lì in bici, e tu ci vai, ma poi scopri che devi essere affiliato a qualche cosa (ciclohobby) che è gratis eh, e manco ti danno un tesserino, e quindi la prossima volta te lo diamo il caffè ma non oggi anche se sei l’unico cretino che è arrivato lì in bici col freddo che c’è.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;il puzzo di inquinamento è asfissiante e insopportabile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i negozi e i negozianti farebbero bene a svegliarsi perché non venderanno più una cippa appena muoiono quelli che ancora non si fidano a usare la carta di credito per gli acquisti online. Sono andato nel negozio di fotografia più professionale di Milano; cercavo un’aggeggio piccolo, inusuale ma sicuramente professionale, e il vecchiaccio che mi ha dato credito (mentre come al solito gli altri del negozio pensavano ai cazzi loro) mi ha detto in modo brusco e scontroso “ueeehhhh mica ce l’abbiamo !!!”. Io ci ho provato a far lavorare questi italiani ma dopo che mi sono fatto 25km di bici in pausa pranzo per andare a trovare ‘staffare qui adesso lo ordino da un venditore cinese su ebay, e in vacca il principio del ‘buy local’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;scientific writing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great insights by &lt;a href="http://www.leancrew.com/all-this/"&gt;drdrang&lt;/a&gt; on Dennis Ritchie (creator of C and co-creator of Unix) who died recently. To me it’s yet another advice on the beauty of scientific writing and the combined effectiveness of brevity clarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scholarly papers have a reputation for dullness, but good ones aren’t dull to people who know, or want to learn, the topic. […]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most C programming books could substitute as boat anchors; K&amp;amp;R is only half an inch thick but always seems to have the answer you’re looking for. […]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The clarity of these guys’ writing is undoubtedly a reflection of the clarity of their thoughts—the same clarity that makes Unix such a pleasure to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="http://www.leancrew.com/all-this/2011/10/dennis-ritchie-unix-and-clarity/"&gt;http://www.leancrew.com/all-this/2011/10/dennis-ritchie-unix-and-clarity/&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;prezzo di un libro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Questi erano degli appunti che avevo preso perché tempo fa mi stupivo del prezzo sproporzionato dei libri in formato Kindle rispetto ai libri veri, su carta. Mi chiedevo dunque quanto del prezzo di un libro cartaceo andasse agli autori, per poi trarre delle conclusioni sul giusto prezzo di un libro elettronico. Non sono mai riuscito a trarne delle conclusioni, anche perché a distanza di quasi tre anni finalmente i prezzi dei libri Kindle è sceso di parecchio tanto.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La vendita di un libro da $20 frutta al publisher (casa editrice?) $10. I costi che sostiene detto publisher sono:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$3: royalties&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$2: printing / binding / paper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$1.20: distribuzione&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$2: marketing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dunque restano $1.80 con cui un publisher deve coprire costi di affitto, editing, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E-books reduce the cost of printing, binding, and paper, but royalties tend to run higher, and all other costs are largely unchanged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(da “Books After Amazon”, di Onnesha Roychoudhuri, &lt;a href="http://www.bostonreview.net/BR35.6/roychoudhuri.php"&gt;http://www.bostonreview.net/&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BR35&lt;/span&gt;.6/roychoudhuri.php&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;usare ipad e iphone sull’aereo&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;F.A.A.&lt;/span&gt; said pilots at the two airlines would not have to shut off and store their iPads during taxiing, takeoff and landing because they had demonstrated that the devices would not impair the functioning of onboard electronics. Alaska Airlines pilots, like passengers, still have to put their iPads away during those critical phases of the flight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(tratto da qualche articolo del New York Times di cui ho perso il link).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;riguardo l’uso di parole come “negro”:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a small publisher, NewSouth Books, announced a new edition of Mark Twain’s “Huckleberry Finn” that will replace its uses of the word “nigger” with “slave”. […]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certainly, as a writer, I see the strength of all the arguments against tinkering with the original, not least because it would be a terrible precedent — start eliminating everything offensive in literary history, and yoùll have little left. But once I returned to the actual novel, I began to feel torn, because I could imagine the effect that its deluge of epithets would have on a young reader, especially a young black reader. (Open the book to the passage in the second chapter that begins, “Strange niggers would stand with their mouths open,” and see if you would be able to read it to a room full of ninth graders.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Huckleberry Finn was intended, of course, as an attack on racism. […]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Da leggere per tutti coloro che s’incagliano sulle parole senza pensare alle azioni.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/08/opinion/08kirsch.html"&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/08/opinion/08kirsch.html&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;la ragnatela&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ovvero, uno strumento di valutazione delle capacità personali di approfondimento.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Domanda: come si può valutare lo sforzo sostenuto da un appassionato di cinema quando ricerca il film perfetto, quello che lo appaga durante le due ore di visione e che lo riempie di emozioni, domande tali da portarlo a rifletterci su anche dopo che sono comparsi i titoli di coda ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Risposta: la ragnatela.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Qui avrei sviluppato l’idea che un film perfetto, a mio parere, è uno talmente interessante che ti spinge a ripensarci su, ripercorrerlo, cercare di immergersi nel suo universo, e quindi continuare dunque a goderselo anche dopo averlo finito di vedere; ad esempio torni a casa e cerchi su internet notizie su attori, dettagli della trama, tecniche di ripresa, idee accennate, interpretazioni varie. Alternativamente, avrei definito la &lt;strong&gt;ragnatela&lt;/strong&gt; come quel sistema che ti permette attraverso riferimenti incrociati di critici autorevoli come Ebert o Scott di rintracciare altri film interessanti, come appunto una ragnatela che intesse il mondo cinematografico collegando piccoli e grandi film degni di essere visti. Onestamente non ricordo più quale delle due idee volessi sviluppare, ma ho lasciato due nomi di film e un link ad una recensione di Roger Ebert, che potrebbero farmi ricordare cosa diavolo intendessi.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;esempi: Junebug, Syriana&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;la &lt;a href="http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20051208/REVIEWS/51130002/1023"&gt;recensione di Syriana&lt;/a&gt; di Roger Ebert&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5041385"&gt;Robert Baer&lt;/a&gt;, agente &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CIA&lt;/span&gt; la cui storia ha ispirato Syriana &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;python and monkeys&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I don’t really know, but that’s how wève always done things around here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La storiella delle scimmie e il legame con la filosofia corporate è divertente ed istruttiva. Leggetela qui: &lt;a href="http://www.b-list.org/weblog/2008/dec/05/python-3000/"&gt;http://www.b-list.org/weblog/2008/dec/05/python-3000/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul Graham racconta una storia simile:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In The Periodic Table, Primo Levi tells a story that happened when he was working in a varnish factory. He was a chemist, and he was fascinated by the fact that the varnish recipe included a raw onion. What could it be for? No one knew; it was just part of the recipe. So he investigated, and eventually discovered that they had started throwing the onion in years ago to test the temperature of the varnish: if it was hot enough, the onion would fry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/arcll1.html"&gt;http://www.paulgraham.com/arcll1.html&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="links"></category><category term="notes"></category></entry><entry><title>olympus c(r)ap lens</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2012-10-12-olympus-cap-lens.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-10-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2012-10-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2012-10-12:/2012-10-12-olympus-cap-lens.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It might be quirky and it might be cool but I would argue this is something which should not appeal to anybody apart from facebook photographers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m talking about the &lt;a href="http://www.petapixel.com/2012/10/11/photographs-shot-using-olympus-quirky-15mm-body-cap-lens"&gt;15mm Olympus body c(r)ap lens&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reasons are two:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;judging from the shots which you can see …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It might be quirky and it might be cool but I would argue this is something which should not appeal to anybody apart from facebook photographers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m talking about the &lt;a href="http://www.petapixel.com/2012/10/11/photographs-shot-using-olympus-quirky-15mm-body-cap-lens"&gt;15mm Olympus body c(r)ap lens&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reasons are two:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;judging from the shots which you can see &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/an_aussie_in_guernsey/sets/72157631683828773/with/8071749336/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; the quality is abysmal. But you have to look at 100%, and while I’m against pixel peeping, when it comes to a technical choice, there is no other way to judge objectively the quality of a lens. This is why I think it may only appeal to facebook photographer, because reduced to web size all photos are sharp and correctly focused (there is a law waiting to be expressed: the lower the resolution of your final output, the less you can spend on equipment, or something like that).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the price is ridiculous ($110). I would then happily recommend buying a &lt;a href="http://www.thephoblographer.com/2011/07/22/review-the-pinwide-pinhole-micro-four-thirds-olympus-ep2-ep3-panasonic-gf3-gh2-g3/"&gt;Pinwide&lt;/a&gt; which sells for forty dollars and makes a completely different kind of photo (real quirky here!, not crappy-quirky) or the wonderful Panasonic 14mm f/2.5 which can be found used for $100 and is &lt;em&gt;tiny&lt;/em&gt; (I recently bought this lens to replace the Olympus 17mm f/2.8 which was starting to get on my nerves with its plasticky silver color).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="photo"></category><category term="gear"></category><category term="links"></category></entry><entry><title>notes on parenting</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2012-08-09-notes-on-parenting.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-08-09T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2012-08-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2012-08-09:/2012-08-09-notes-on-parenting.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Lately I’ve been reading quite a lof of articles about parenting. Most of them are book reviews but I did not read any of these books though&lt;sup id="fnref:nota-zecchi"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:nota-zecchi"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which could mean: (A) I’m a bit shallow, (B) stressed out New Yorkers, overproductive Chinese immigrants, rich Californians are not …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Lately I’ve been reading quite a lof of articles about parenting. Most of them are book reviews but I did not read any of these books though&lt;sup id="fnref:nota-zecchi"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:nota-zecchi"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which could mean: (A) I’m a bit shallow, (B) stressed out New Yorkers, overproductive Chinese immigrants, rich Californians are not people that I feel entitled to give me directions on how to raise my kid (even though I acknowledge their superior education and intelligence and that their sons and daughters will surely rule the world).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, these articles are (as usual) very well written and are full of ideas that I have enjoyed. I want to keep updating this post every time I find something good. They may also help a future me because you never know what’s behind the corner of becoming a dad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;excerpt 1: “Spoiled Rotten” by Elizabeth Kolbert&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;L.A.&lt;/span&gt; families observed, no child routinely performed household chores without being instructed to. Often, the kids had to be begged to attempt the simplest tasks; often, they still refused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Yanira had no clear role in the group, she quickly found ways to make herself useful. Twice a day, she swept the sand off the sleeping mats, and she helped stack the kapashi leaves for transport back to the village. In the evening, she fished for crustaceans, which she cleaned, boiled, and served to the others. Calm and self-possessed, Yanira “asked for nothing,” Izquierdo later recalled. The girl’s behavior made a strong impression on the anthropologist because at the time of the trip Yanira was just six years old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Most parents today were brought up in a culture that put a strong emphasis on being special, (…) being special takes hard work and can’t be trusted to children. Hence the exhausting cycle of constantly monitoring their work and performance, which in turn makes children feel less competent and confident, so that they need even more oversight.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(…) today’s incoming freshmen are less likely to be concerned about the rigors of higher education than “about how they will handle the logistics of everyday life”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Children, according to “Life at Home,” are disproportionate generators of clutter: “Each new child in a household leads to a 30 percent increase in a family’s inventory of possessions during the preschool years alone.” Many of the kids’ rooms pictured are so crowded with clothes and toys, so many of which have been tossed on the floor, that there is no path to the bed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Source:  &lt;a href="http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/books/2012/07/02/120702crbo_books_kolbert"&gt;http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/books/2012/07/02/120702crbo_books_kolbert&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;excerpt 2: “Raising Successful Children” by Madeline Levine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central task of growing up is to develop a sense of self that is autonomous, confident and generally in accord with reality. If you treat your walking toddler as if she can’t walk, you diminish her confidence and distort reality. Ditto nightly “reviews” of homework, repetitive phone calls to “just check if you’re O.K.” and “editing” (read: writing) your child’s college application essay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hanging back and allowing children to make mistakes is one of the greatest challenges of parenting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having tutors prep your anxious 3-year-old for a preschool interview because all your friends’ children are going to this particular school or pushing your exhausted child to take one more advanced-placement course because it will ensure her spot as class valedictorian is not involved parenting but toxic overparenting aimed at meeting the parents’ need for status or affirmation and not the child’s needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(…) the child’s job is to grow, yours is to control your anxiety so it doesn’t get in the way of his reasonable moves toward autonomy (…)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parents also have to make sure their own lives are fulfilling. There is no parent more vulnerable to the excesses of overparenting than an unhappy parent One of the most important things we do for our children is to present them with a version of adult life that is appealing and worth striving for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Source: &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/08/05/opinion/sunday/raising-successful-children.html"&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/2012/08/05/opinion/sunday/raising-successful-children.html&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;excerpt 3: “How to Raise a Child” By Judith Warner&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(…) schools that worship at the altar of high achievement but do everything they can to undermine children’s growth and well-being: eliminating recess; assigning mind-deadening amounts of homework; and ranking, measuring and valuing kids by narrowly focused test scores, while cutting out other areas of creative education in which large numbers of students who don’t necessarily test well might find success and thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(…) the inconvenient truth remains that not every child can be shaped and accelerated into Harvard material. But all kids can have their spirits broken, depression induced and anxiety stoked by too much stress, too little downtime and too much attention given to external factors that make them look good to an audience of appraising eyes but leave them feeling rotten inside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Source: &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/07/29/books/review/teach-your-children-well-by-madeline-levine.html"&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/2012/07/29/books/review/teach-your-children-well-by-madeline-levine.html&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;excerpt 4: “America’s Top Parent - What’s behind the Tiger Mother craze?”  by Elizabeth Kolbert&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chua, the daughter of Chinese immigrants, is a Yale Law School professor. She is married to another Yale law professor and has two daughters, whom she drives relentlessly (…) In Chua’s binary world, there are just two kinds of mother. There are “Chinese mothers,” who, she allows, do not necessarily have to be Chinese (…) Then, there are “Western” mothers. (…) Chua chooses the instruments that her daughters will play and stands over them as they practice for three, four, sometimes five hours at a stretch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Yes, you can brute-force any kid to learn to play the piano—just precisely like his or her billion neighbors” is how one of the comments on the Wall Street Journal’s Web site put it. “But you’ll never get a Jimi Hendrix that way”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just about the only category in which American students outperform the competition is self-regard (…)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parenting is hard. As anyone who has gone through the process and had enough leisure (and still functioning brain cells) to reflect on it knows, a lot of it is a crapshoot. Things go wrong that you have no control over, and, on occasion, things also go right, and you have no control over those, either. The experience is scary and exhilarating and often humiliating, not because you’re disappointed in your kids, necessarily, but because you’re disappointed in yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Source: &lt;a href="http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/books/2011/01/31/110131crbo_books_kolbert"&gt;http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/books/2011/01/31/110131crbo_books_kolbert&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:nota-zecchi"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only book I’ve read is by an italian philosophy professor, Stefano Zecchi, who recounts a nice tale about parenting at a late age, being frequently mistaken by his son’s grandfather, and some clever observations on the declining importance of the dad in today’s family. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:nota-zecchi" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="quote"></category><category term="links"></category><category term="notes"></category></entry><entry><title>talking photography</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2012-07-26-talking-photography.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-07-26T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2012-07-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2012-07-26:/2012-07-26-talking-photography.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are still pearls to be found on the internet, &lt;a href="http://aadm.github.io/2012-06-02-these-tech-writers-invettiva.html"&gt;after all&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these days I have found three photography blogs which are full of interesting and well written articles; stimulating, instructive, much better of the crap that Popular Photography publishes (and I’m not even mentioning the countless websites …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are still pearls to be found on the internet, &lt;a href="http://aadm.github.io/2012-06-02-these-tech-writers-invettiva.html"&gt;after all&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these days I have found three photography blogs which are full of interesting and well written articles; stimulating, instructive, much better of the crap that Popular Photography publishes (and I’m not even mentioning the countless websites and blogs of pixel-peepers and technology feticists).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worth bookmarking them for when you have time to sit down and read something that will help renew your passion for this art:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://blog.mingthein.com"&gt;http://blog.mingthein.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ultrasomething.com/photography"&gt;http://www.ultrasomething.com/photography&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.laroquephoto.com/blog"&gt;http://www.laroquephoto.com/blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the favourite articles that I have read so far:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ultrasomething.com/photography/2012/06/hatch-battening"&gt;http://www.ultrasomething.com/photography/2012/06/hatch-battening&lt;/a&gt;: I was one of the guys throwing shit at Leica for their Monochrom camera, sold at an outrageous price. I am still strongly opposed in principle to Leicas and in particular to this model on the basis of pricing alone, because I think it’s strongly driven by brand and marketing more than technology, but at least now I understand there may something more behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ultrasomething.com/photography/2011/12/black-and-white-colors"&gt;http://www.ultrasomething.com/photography/2011/12/black-and-white-colors&lt;/a&gt;: a little story of how to assign a task to yourself to overcome conventional approaches and get an alternative view of reality. It also transforms into a story of how little day-to-day creativity will not pay you off in material terms but will give you something much more important in the long term (sense of accomplishment, etc.). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://blog.mingthein.com/2012/07/21/street-photography-ethics"&gt;http://blog.mingthein.com/2012/07/21/street-photography-ethics&lt;/a&gt;: this guy is not a poet like Egor but knows a thing or two about technique, plus I dig his street shoots. He’s a hyper-nerd anyway, just look at his &lt;a href="http://blog.mingthein.com/equipmentdatabase/"&gt;camerapedia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ultrasomething.com/photography/2012/02/gear-guano-canal"&gt;http://www.ultrasomething.com/photography/2012/02/gear-guano-canal&lt;/a&gt;: another very well written tale on how photographers (or maybe I should say “men”) are primarily brainless gadget-freak addicts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://blog.leica-camera.com/photographers/blog-contributors/egor/fegor-shooting-through-the-wormhole"&gt;http://blog.leica-camera.com/photographers/blog-contributors/egor/fegor-shooting-through-the-wormhole&lt;/a&gt;: unexpected praise of pinhole photography — again this is to me a piece full of stimulating thoughts, not because I have any interest in pinhole photography &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt; but as an excuse for exploring new ideas and new point of views; the message that I got from this is “get rid of the excess baggage that is the technical excellence, the supersharp definition of an 85mm f/1.4, the extreme detail that a Nikon D800 may give you, and try to find a certain meaning in your pictures, whatever that might be”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.laroquephoto.com/blog/2012/7/19/seeing-mono.html"&gt;http://www.laroquephoto.com/blog/2012/7/19/seeing-mono.html&lt;/a&gt;: it may seem just a little description on how to get some good black and whites, but at the beginning of it a very important point is stated, that all the images that we see on this blog (and, one assumes, also on all the other websites of photographers who know something) are processed and nothing that arrives to the public is ever, truly &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OOC&lt;/span&gt; (straight out of camera): &lt;em&gt;“Processing images is as old as photography itself”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="links"></category><category term="photo"></category></entry><entry><title>photography in space</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2012-05-02-photography-in-space.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-05-02T03:51:00+02:00</published><updated>2012-05-02T03:51:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2012-05-02:/2012-05-02-photography-in-space.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you have love of photography and are a dreamy nerd enamored of Asimov’s books, you really need to read this; it’s an account by a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NASA&lt;/span&gt; astronaut about the daily experiences of shooting photographs in space:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.luminous-landscape.com/locations/photography_in_space.shtml"&gt;http://www.luminous-landscape.com/locations/photography_in_space.shtml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you have love of photography and are a dreamy nerd enamored of Asimov’s books, you really need to read this; it’s an account by a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NASA&lt;/span&gt; astronaut about the daily experiences of shooting photographs in space:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.luminous-landscape.com/locations/photography_in_space.shtml"&gt;http://www.luminous-landscape.com/locations/photography_in_space.shtml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="links"></category></entry><entry><title>reading fiction is important</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2012-04-18-reading-fiction-is-important.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-04-18T09:03:12+02:00</published><updated>2012-04-18T09:03:12+02:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2012-04-18:/2012-04-18-reading-fiction-is-important.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So true:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading fiction is important. It is a vital means of imagining a life other than our own, which in turn makes us more empathetic beings. Following complex story lines stretches our brains beyond the 140 characters of sound-bite thinking, and staying within the world of a novel gives …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So true:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading fiction is important. It is a vital means of imagining a life other than our own, which in turn makes us more empathetic beings. Following complex story lines stretches our brains beyond the 140 characters of sound-bite thinking, and staying within the world of a novel gives us the ability to be quiet and alone, two skills that are disappearing faster than the polar icecaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ann Patchett, from &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/04/18/opinion/and-the-winner-of-the-pulitzer-isnt.html"&gt;yesterday’s New York Times&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="links"></category><category term="quote"></category></entry><entry><title>brainpickings</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2012-02-14-brainpickings.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-02-14T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-02-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2012-02-14:/2012-02-14-brainpickings.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ho scoperto un sito fantastico, di quelli che ti fanno riscoprire quanto Internet possa ancora essere fonte di meraviglie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Si chiama &lt;a href="http://www.brainpickings.org"&gt;Brain Pickings&lt;/a&gt; ed è come se fossero i ritagli di giornale che vorresti mettere da parte; parla di creatività, di scienza, di filosofia, di psicologia; parla di qualsiasi argomento …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ho scoperto un sito fantastico, di quelli che ti fanno riscoprire quanto Internet possa ancora essere fonte di meraviglie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Si chiama &lt;a href="http://www.brainpickings.org"&gt;Brain Pickings&lt;/a&gt; ed è come se fossero i ritagli di giornale che vorresti mettere da parte; parla di creatività, di scienza, di filosofia, di psicologia; parla di qualsiasi argomento interessi la sua creatrice Maria Popova, di qualsiasi cosa che stimoli la sua curiosità. Come dice il sito stesso, Brain Pickings è “uno scrigno del tesoro fatto di mattoncini &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E in quest’epoca in cui si scopre che Google, dopo tutto, è malvagio come qualsiasi altra mega corporation; in cui non si parla più di &lt;em&gt;amici&lt;/em&gt; perché i &lt;em&gt;friends&lt;/em&gt; ormai sono quelli di Facebook; in cui stimati giornalisti si affidano a Twitter per fare del reportage; in cui i blog più famosi ti danno contenuti superficiali in cambio di qualche click — e nel frattempo raccolgono informazioni su cosa compri, cosa mangi, con chi esci&lt;sup id="fnref:nota"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:nota"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;; in quest’epoca è piacevole imbattersi in un sito fatto con cura, che ti arricchisce, ed è assolutamente privo di pubblicità o secondi fini. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La newsletter di finesettimana poi è una delizia, perché riporta gli articoli completi e quindi permette una lettura tranquilla, senza costringerti ad inseguire i links.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nell’ultima edizione c’è un bellissimo articolo che mi ha fatto scoprire questi &lt;a href="http://www.brainpickings.org/index.php/2012/02/07/david-ogilvy-on-writing/"&gt;10 consigli per scrivere bene di David Ogilvy&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Utili secondo me sia per chi vuol migliorare la propria capacità di scrivere bene sia materiale tecnico (rapporti lavorativi ad esempio) che non (blogs, racconti di viaggio, recensioni di videogiochi).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non li traduco in italiano per timore di denudarli della loro efficacia:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The better you write, the higher you go in Ogilvy &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Mather. People who think well, write well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Woolly minded people write woolly memos, woolly letters and woolly speeches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good writing is not a natural gift. You have to learn to write well. Here are 10 hints:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read the Roman-Raphaelson book on writing. Read it three times.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write the way you talk. Naturally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use short words, short sentences and short paragraphs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Never use jargon words like reconceptualize, demassification, attitudinally, judgmentally. They are hallmarks of a pretentious ass.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Never write more than two pages on any subject.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check your quotations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Never send a letter or a memo on the day you write it. Read it aloud the next morning — and then edit it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it is something important, get a colleague to improve it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Before you send your letter or your memo, make sure it is crystal clear what you want the recipient to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you want &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACTION&lt;/span&gt;, don’t write. Go and tell the guy what you want.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fonti:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.listsofnote.com/2012/02/how-to-write.html"&gt;http://www.listsofnote.com/2012/02/how-to-write.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.brainpickings.org/index.php/2012/02/07/david-ogilvy-on-writing/"&gt;http://www.brainpickings.org/index.php/2012/02/07/david-ogilvy-on-writing/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:nota"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A tale proposito, consiglio la lettura di un paio di articoli che parlano di “Big Data”: &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/02/12/sunday-review/big-datas-impact-in-the-world.html?_r=1&amp;amp;pagewanted=all"&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/2012/02/12/sunday-review/big-datas-impact-in-the-world.html&lt;/a&gt;,  &lt;a href="http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/10/24/big-data/"&gt;http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/10/24/big-data/&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:nota" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="notes"></category><category term="links"></category><category term="quote"></category></entry><entry><title>hereditary genius</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2011-03-14-hereditary-genius.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-03-14T09:04:00+01:00</published><updated>2011-03-14T09:04:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2011-03-14:/2011-03-14-hereditary-genius.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2011/02/20/magazine/mind-secrets.html"&gt;“Secrets of a Mind-Gamer”&lt;/a&gt;, a fascinating article on a normal guy who becomes a memory champion:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his 1869 book &lt;em&gt;Hereditary Genius&lt;/em&gt; Sir Francis Galton argued that a person
could improve at mental and physical activities until he hit a wall, which “he
cannot by any education or exertion …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2011/02/20/magazine/mind-secrets.html"&gt;“Secrets of a Mind-Gamer”&lt;/a&gt;, a fascinating article on a normal guy who becomes a memory champion:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his 1869 book &lt;em&gt;Hereditary Genius&lt;/em&gt; Sir Francis Galton argued that a person
could improve at mental and physical activities until he hit a wall, which “he
cannot by any education or exertion overpass.” In other words, the best we can
do is simply the best we can do. But Ericsson and his colleagues have found
over and over again that with the right kind of effort, that’s rarely the
case. They believe that Galton’s wall often has much less to do with our
innate limits than with what we consider an acceptable level of performance.  They’ve found that top achievers typically follow the same general pattern.
They develop strategies for keeping out of the autonomous stage by doing three
things: focusing on their technique, staying goal-oriented and getting
immediate feedback on their performance […] To improve, we have to be
constantly pushing ourselves beyond where we think our limits lie and then pay
attention to how and why we fail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="quote"></category><category term="links"></category></entry><entry><title>making a really good coffee</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2011-03-08-making-a-really-good-coffee.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-03-08T23:08:00+01:00</published><updated>2011-03-08T23:08:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2011-03-08:/2011-03-08-making-a-really-good-coffee.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;Making a really good coffee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=science-in-the-neighborhood-how-to-2011-03-08"&gt;Interesting post on Scientific American&lt;/a&gt;, however this barista needs a reality check: a refractometer to make coffee ? I’d recommend a couple of place in my hometown (Bari) where
baristas have no PhD but make the best coffee ever.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;Making a really good coffee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.scientificamerican.com/blog/post.cfm?id=science-in-the-neighborhood-how-to-2011-03-08"&gt;Interesting post on Scientific American&lt;/a&gt;, however this barista needs a reality check: a refractometer to make coffee ? I’d recommend a couple of place in my hometown (Bari) where
baristas have no PhD but make the best coffee ever.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="links"></category><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>stutterer writes about stuttering</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2011-02-24-stutterer-writes-about-stuttering.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-02-24T21:10:00+01:00</published><updated>2011-02-24T21:10:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2011-02-24:/2011-02-24-stutterer-writes-about-stuttering.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/assessment/2011/02/the_stutterer.html"&gt;great article on Slate.com&lt;/a&gt;: taking inspiration from “King’s speech”, a stutterer writes about stuttering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some great insights, worth reading if you are vaguely interested in the subject (or if you have a friend who stammers and want to know what on earth does he think when he …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/assessment/2011/02/the_stutterer.html"&gt;great article on Slate.com&lt;/a&gt;: taking inspiration from “King’s speech”, a stutterer writes about stuttering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some great insights, worth reading if you are vaguely interested in the subject (or if you have a friend who stammers and want to know what on earth does he think when he’s stuck on a word).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="links"></category></entry><entry><title>dunbar number</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2010-12-26-dunbar-number.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-12-26T23:58:00+01:00</published><updated>2010-12-26T23:58:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2010-12-26:/2010-12-26-dunbar-number.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/12/26/opinion/26dunbar.html"&gt;150 friends (Dunbar’s number)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have deleted &lt;a href="http://aadm.github.io/2010-08-03-farewell-facebook.html"&gt;my Facebook account a long time ago&lt;/a&gt; and I can confirm that I can live very happily with no Facebook around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article by Robin Dunbar (did you know about “Dunbar’s number” ?) is very
interesting however. It does say that Facebook …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/12/26/opinion/26dunbar.html"&gt;150 friends (Dunbar’s number)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have deleted &lt;a href="http://aadm.github.io/2010-08-03-farewell-facebook.html"&gt;my Facebook account a long time ago&lt;/a&gt; and I can confirm that I can live very happily with no Facebook around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article by Robin Dunbar (did you know about “Dunbar’s number” ?) is very
interesting however. It does say that Facebook can be a positive thing. But it
also says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, you can “friend” 500, 1,000, even 5,000 people with your Facebook page,
but all save the core 150 are mere voyeurs looking into your daily life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="quote"></category><category term="links"></category></entry><entry><title>la repubblica vs new york times</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2009-09-01-la-repubblica-vs-new-york-times.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-09-01T23:21:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-09-01T23:21:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2009-09-01:/2009-09-01-la-repubblica-vs-new-york-times.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Il 29 agosto 2009 il New York Times pubblica un articolo di Amy Cortese, “&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/08/30/business/30shoe.html"&gt;Wiggling Their Toes at the Shoe Giants&lt;/a&gt;“.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Il 31 agosto sul sito della Repubblica trovo un pezzo di Federico Rampini, “&lt;a href="http://www.repubblica.it/2009/08/sezioni/esteri/scarpe-dita/scarpe-dita/scarpe-dita.html"&gt;Le scarpe con le dita hanno conquistato l’America&lt;/a&gt;“.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lo leggo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sensazione di déjà vu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lo …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Il 29 agosto 2009 il New York Times pubblica un articolo di Amy Cortese, “&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/08/30/business/30shoe.html"&gt;Wiggling Their Toes at the Shoe Giants&lt;/a&gt;“.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Il 31 agosto sul sito della Repubblica trovo un pezzo di Federico Rampini, “&lt;a href="http://www.repubblica.it/2009/08/sezioni/esteri/scarpe-dita/scarpe-dita/scarpe-dita.html"&gt;Le scarpe con le dita hanno conquistato l’America&lt;/a&gt;“.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lo leggo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sensazione di déjà vu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lo rileggo, e lo confronto con l’articolo del New York Times. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Articoli a confronto&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vibram con la linea Five Fingers […] ha visto le sue vendite triplicare ogni anno, dopo il lancio nel 2006.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vibram says sales of its FiveFingers have tripled every year since they were introduced in 2006 […]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ora tremano i colossi, che rappresentano un fatturato annuo da 17 miliardi di dollari.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[…] significant impact on not only running shoes but also on the broader $17 billion sports shoe market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Daniel Lieberman, docente di biologia evolutiva a Harvard, è uno degli scienziati che sostiene la “scarpa invisibile”. […] “Non esistono prove che le scarpe sportive abbiano migliorato la condizione di chi corre”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;There’s not a lot of evidence that runing shoes have made people better off”, said Daniel E. Lieberman, a professor of human evolutionary biology at Harvard […]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;È arrivato alla stessa conclusione il medico Craig Richards della facoltà di medicina di Newcastle in Australia, il cui studio sarà pubblicato sul British Journal of Sports Medicine: “Non esiste una sola indagine clinica che abbia dimostrato i benefici delle scarpe molleggiate o protettive, nel prevenire i danni fisici o nel migliorare i risultati sportivi”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Craig Richards, a researcher at the School of Medicine and Public Health at the University of Newcastle in Australia […] could not find a single clinical study showing that cushioned or corrective running shoes prevented injury or improved performance. His findings were published last year in The British Journal of Sports Medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Il loro idolo era Abebe Bikila, il leggendario maratoneta etiope che vinse alle Olimpiadi di Roma del 1960 correndo a piedi nudi.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently, at the 1960 Summer Olympics in Rome, Abebe Bikila, an Ethiopian runner, caused a stir when he ran the marathon barefoot and won.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;La stessa Vibram quando inventò la linea Cinque Dita all’inizio pensava di rivolgersi a nicchie di mercato come gli appassionati di kayak o di yoga.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Vibram, an Italian company known for its rugged rubber soles, designed the FiveFingers a few years ago, company officials figured that they would appeal to boaters, kayakers and yogis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lo si deve al successo di nuovi metodi di allenamento - ChiRunning e Pose Method - popolarizzato nei paesi angloamericani da un best-seller, “Born to Run”, cioè nati per correre.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But popular training methods like ChiRunning and the Pose Method that promote a more “natural” gait, as well as “Born to Run,” a best-selling new book about long-distance running by Christopher McDougall, have helped spur interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Perciò il nostro piede è uno strumento che l’evoluzione delle specie ha disegnato alla perfezione: per sostenerci nella corsa, ed anche come “sensore” di tutte le asperità del terreno, pronto a segnalarci i pericoli che possono rappresentare per la nostra salute.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proponents of this approach contend that naked feet are perfectly capable of running long distances, and that encasing them in the fortress of modern footwear weakens foot muscles and ligaments and blocks vital sensory input about terrain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Galahad Clark, fondatore a Londra di Terra Plana che è un altro produttore di “scarpe invisibili”, trae la conclusione: le superscarpe tecnologiche vendute dai colossi dell’abbigliamento sportivo “sono come delle bare, imprigionano il piede e gli impediscono di svolgere le sue funzioni essenziali”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The shoe arguably got in the way of evolution,” said Galahad Clark, a seventh-generation shoemaker and chief executive of the shoemaker Terra Plana, based in London. “They’re like little foot coffins that stopped the foot from working the way it’s supposed to work.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;È in totale disaccordo Lewis Maharam, consulente medico dei New York Road Runners (il club dei maratoneti newyorchesi): “Correre a piedi nudi va bene per chi ha una costituzione bio-meccanica perfetta, per il restante 95% della popolazione è una ricetta sicura per finire all’ospedale”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In 95 percent of the population or higher, running barefoot will land you in my office,” said Dr. Lewis G. Maharam, medical director for the New York Road Runners, the group that organizes the New York City Marathon. “A very small number of people are biomechanically perfect,” he said, so most need some sort of supportive or corrective footwear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Rampini dovrebbe citare il New York Times per danni&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mi stupisco che non l’abbia ancora fatto. Un chiaro esempio di plagio. Certo, la povera Amy Cortese non ha il dono della sintesi di Rampini; scopiazzando gli appunti segreti del giornalista italiano, riempe il suo articolo di troppi dettagli (nomi, fatti, numeri) su cui il ‘nostro’ non si sofferma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Per non parlare degli errori da novellina della povera Amy. Ad esempio, parlando del dr.Craig Richards scrive che i risultati della sua ricerca sono stati pubblicati lo scorso anno nel British Journal of Sports Medicine, sbagliando clamorosamente i tempi; infatti, dice Rampini, tale studio “sarà pubblicato sul British Journal of Sports Medicine”. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imbarazzante constatare la scarsa affidabilità della stessa rivista scientifica, visto che sul loro sito risulta che la data di pubblicazione dell’articolo in questione (&lt;a href="http://bjsm.bmj.com/cgi/content/short/43/3/159"&gt;“Is your prescription of distance running shoes evidence-based ?”&lt;/a&gt;) risale ad aprile 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Infine stendiamo il proverbiale velo sulla conoscenza della lingua italiana di Amy Cortese. Quando infatti Rampini scrive:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;L’autore del libro ‘Born to Run’, Christopher McDougall, ricorda che l’essere umano è una macchina geneticamente programmata per la corsa: è così che i nostri antenati sono sopravvissuti alle belve feroci che li braccavano, e a loro volta hanno potuto alimentarsi di selvaggina.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La giornalista del New York Times riporta:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Lieberman’s research suggests that two million years ago, our ancestors’ ability to run long distances helped them outlast their prey […]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sbagliando quindi sia l’attribuzione della frase (non lo scrittore McDougall ma il prof. Lieberman) che il significato stesso; si è mai sentito di un uomo preistorico che grazie alla capacità di correre a lungo riusciva a sfiancare la sua vittima (&lt;em&gt;prey&lt;/em&gt;) ? Macché… meno male che c’è Rampini a dirci invece che l’uomo preistorico correva per sfuggire alle “belve feroci” (&lt;em&gt;predators&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Giustizia è fatta&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consiglio all’autorevole &lt;a href="http://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federico_Rampini"&gt;Rampini&lt;/a&gt; di mettersi al riparo da eventuali dubbi di plagio che potrebbero ritorcersi contro di lui sulla base delle date di pubblicazione dei due articoli citando, ad esempio, tutte le fonti a cui ha attinto per scrivere questo suo pezzo.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="notes"></category><category term="links"></category></entry><entry><title>new york times on geothermal energy</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2009-06-25-new-york-times-on-geothermal-energy.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-06-25T12:29:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-06-25T12:29:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2009-06-25:/2009-06-25-new-york-times-on-geothermal-energy.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the article: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/06/24/business/energy-environment/24geotherm.html"&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/2009/06/24/business/energy-environment/24geotherm.html&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is one very nice and informed comment from a PhD student that puts things into the right perspective:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) The major difference between enhanced geothermal and standard oil and gas extraction is the …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the article: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/06/24/business/energy-environment/24geotherm.html"&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/2009/06/24/business/energy-environment/24geotherm.html&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is one very nice and informed comment from a PhD student that puts things into the right perspective:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) The major difference between enhanced geothermal and standard oil and gas extraction is the high pressures used to create geothermal reservoirs. Oil and gas are normally extracted from porous sedimentary rocks (10-30% void space), but the heat fluxes required for geothermal are found in volcanic rocks with less than 1% void space. The rock must be fractured to allow water to flow through it, and it is this process that causes earthquakes. The earthquakes can continue for months after the pressure has been released because the Earth is a dynamic place and not all of the stress transfer is instantaneous; in fact, the later-occurring quakes are usually governed by stress changes caused by diffusion (slow filtering through the limited porosity due to pressure gradients) rather than advection (the injection velocity/pressure, which causes the immediate earthquakes.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2) There is no danger of creating “new tectonic plates”; the tectonic plates are on a completely different scale than a single geothermal reservoir (1000s vs 1s of kilometers). The absolute worst case scenario would be changing the stress regime enough to reactivate an existing tectonic-scale fault like the San Andreas/San Jacinto etc., which is very unlikely due to the scale difference.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3) For risk assessment purposes, risk is the product of hazard (the event that might be triggered) and vulnerability. A project like this ends up going forward because when the hazard is large (i.e. it is very likely that you will trigger small earthquakes), the vulnerability is also low since it will only affect a relatively sparsely populated area immediately nearby. Obviously, if you happen to live in that area, that is not a reassuring argument. In the other extreme case, if the vulnerability is high (eg. a Landers earthquake-type rupture across most of SoCal), the hazard is low (the chance of re-activating the San Andreas is slim). In both cases, the product of the two works out to a small number, so the risk is deemed acceptable. The soft underbelly of risk assessment is that seismic hazard is fiendishly difficult to quantify given present methodology and observational capabilities.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4) Regional seismic hazard and geothermal energy will continue to be coupled since the areas with the highest geothermal gradients (rate of temperature increase with depth) tend to be tectonically active (young or recently deformed) crust. However, the potential benefits to figuring out geothermal energy are myriad - clean, reliable, domestic supplies - and I think it’s worth pursuing. An exciting tangential scientific opportunity also exists: if we can figure out the processes that control microseismicity in reservoirs, we will be much closer to predicting and someday mitigating the types of earthquakes that make headlines on a more regular basis.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5) This may come as a surprise, but the largest geothermal producer in the world is the oil giant Chevron; they have several enormous traditional geothermal projects in Indonesia.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://community.nytimes.com/comments/www.nytimes.com/2009/06/24/business/energy-environment/24geotherm.html?permid=48#comment48"&gt;[click here for the original comment]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="notes"></category><category term="links"></category></entry></feed>