<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>aadm - movies</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://aadm.github.io/feeds/movies.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://aadm.github.io/</id><updated>2011-01-19T23:56:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>frozen the worst movie ever</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2011-01-19-frozen-the-worst-movie-ever.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-01-19T23:56:00+01:00</published><updated>2011-01-19T23:56:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2011-01-19:/2011-01-19-frozen-the-worst-movie-ever.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is probably one of the worst movie I’ve ever watched. It is so bad that I
actually enjoyed it. But the most incredible thing is that the three reviews
that I’ve read, well they’re not so harsh on this piece of junk:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emma Bell, in particular, really sells the terror of their predicament (…) I
don’t …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is probably one of the worst movie I’ve ever watched. It is so bad that I
actually enjoyed it. But the most incredible thing is that the three reviews
that I’ve read, well they’re not so harsh on this piece of junk:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emma Bell, in particular, really sells the terror of their predicament (…) I
don’t think I’ve seen a movie this tense since The Descent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(source: &lt;a href="http://www.filmjunk.com/2010/02/06/frozen-review"&gt;http://www.filmjunk.com/2010/02/06/frozen-review&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(…) a nifty little chiller that balances its cold terrain with an
unexpectedly warm heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(source: &lt;a href="http://movies.nytimes.com/2010/02/05/movies/05frozen.html"&gt;http://movies.nytimes.com/2010/02/05/movies/05frozen.html&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if this is not enough, there’s also the &lt;a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/marshall-fine/huffpost-review-ifrozeni_b_450620.html"&gt;Huffington Post’s review&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to say, it will be hard to trust &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NYT&lt;/span&gt; reviews from now on.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="movies"></category></entry><entry><title>twentyfour</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2010-06-15-twentyfour.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-06-15T22:02:00+02:00</published><updated>2010-06-15T22:02:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2010-06-15:/2010-06-15-twentyfour.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been a &lt;a href="http://aadm.github.io/2007-02-13-24-talk.html"&gt;great fan of 24&lt;/a&gt; since its first season, years ago. I’ve thoroughly enjoyed the first season, and also the second and the third. However, the show has been moving towards full improbability with the latest seasons. I think I also watched season 4, and then I don’t remember anymore; maybe I’ve also seen …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been a &lt;a href="http://aadm.github.io/2007-02-13-24-talk.html"&gt;great fan of 24&lt;/a&gt; since its first season, years ago. I’ve thoroughly enjoyed the first season, and also the second and the third. However, the show has been moving towards full improbability with the latest seasons. I think I also watched season 4, and then I don’t remember anymore; maybe I’ve also seen season 5, but maybe I slept through some of the episodes — I honestly don’t recall. And then I didn’t even know they made yet another season (number six), and now I can’t be bothered finding out more about it even less watch it.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suppose that’s very bad for a show that started out so well and got me gripped for all the 24 episodes of its first season; I do remember long nights watching six or seven episodes one after the other.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then something broke. These twenty-four episodes began to seem like a drag: and I actually fell asleep while Jack tortured yet another terrorist. Compare to the Sopranos or Dexter; twelve episodes for seasons, characters that are interesting and evolve through all these seasons and when there’s nothing else to say then stop it for chrissake (the Sopranos rule here; Dexter goes on its 4th season now, I hope it won’t be disappointing).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: I wrote this in August 2009, when season 7 was just announced. I also wrote: “So here comes season 7; will there be a change in 24 ? Will it grip me once again ? I don’t know, but for now I really enjoyed the debate about the use of torture in the series”. And about this last point, there are two really good documentaries that are worth watching: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HBO&lt;/span&gt;’s “Abu Ghraib” and Errol Morris’ “Standard Operating Procedure”.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.newyorker.com/reporting/2007/02/19/070219fa_fact_mayer"&gt;Whatever it takes&lt;/a&gt;, by Jane Mayer. The New Yorker, 19 February 2007.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/01/08/arts/television/08fox.html"&gt;New Era in Politics, New Focus for 24&lt;/a&gt;, by Edward Wyatt, 7 January 2009.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="movies"></category><category term="tv"></category></entry><entry><title>mountain bike movies</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2010-05-05-mountain-bike-movies.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-05-05T23:03:00+02:00</published><updated>2010-05-05T23:03:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2010-05-05:/2010-05-05-mountain-bike-movies.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am an enthusiast mountain bike rider, but because I seem to be affected by a number of injuries associated with slow recovery times (my old age plays a big part here, as it is &lt;em&gt;physiologically&lt;/em&gt; proven that is faster to recover from a broken bone when you’re 20 than if you’re approaching your 40s), I don’t …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am an enthusiast mountain bike rider, but because I seem to be affected by a number of injuries associated with slow recovery times (my old age plays a big part here, as it is &lt;em&gt;physiologically&lt;/em&gt; proven that is faster to recover from a broken bone when you’re 20 than if you’re approaching your 40s), I don’t get as much time riding my bike as I’d like to.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that’s why I enjoy mountain bike movies; and I’m pretty sure that I’m not alone here, and plenty of other people like watching this sort of things because, apart from professionals, &lt;em&gt;nobody&lt;/em&gt; really rides as much as they like.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately I was watching “The Ride” (link here), and it was pretty boring to watch these nice shots of youngsters ripping off their downhill bikes, big jumps, fast pedalling and all. Then, in the second half od the movie there was first an incredibly cute 5-yr old kid who was interviewed like he was a pro, and filmed while he was pedaling on his mini-bike around skateparks and mini-dirt trails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That kid was cute but it’s got nothing to do with the point I want to make here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later on in the movie, there’s the point: it was an older guy, sunglasses, head shaved and killer attitiude that began to tell his story of when he had this idea of doing a gap jump over a train.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that’s what really hooked me; the older guy, not the young kids.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="cycling"></category><category term="movies"></category></entry><entry><title>punch drunk love minireview</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2005-11-04-punch-drunk-love-minireview.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2005-11-04T15:36:00+01:00</published><updated>2005-11-04T15:36:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2005-11-04:/2005-11-04-punch-drunk-love-minireview.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Punch Drunk Love, a.k.a. il lato oscuro di Adam Sandler.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C’e’ un lui che e’ schizzato. Schizzato di brutto. Ma all’inizio non sembra.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E’ gentile coi suoi colleghi di lavoro, si mette giacca e cravatta, dice sempre si’ alle sorelle rompipalle.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ma !  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ma dice di no ad una tipa che vuole uscire con lui. Ed e …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Punch Drunk Love, a.k.a. il lato oscuro di Adam Sandler.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C’e’ un lui che e’ schizzato. Schizzato di brutto. Ma all’inizio non sembra.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E’ gentile coi suoi colleghi di lavoro, si mette giacca e cravatta, dice sempre si’ alle sorelle rompipalle.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ma !  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ma dice di no ad una tipa che vuole uscire con lui. Ed e’ pieno di tic. Quindi tu inizi a sospettare che lui e’ schizzato. Poi una sera va a cena dalle sorelle rompipalle, qualcuno dice qualcosa, e lui distrugge una vetrata in un moto violento dall’incredibile potere cinematografico.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, e’ schizzato. Ma e’ simpatico, tifi per lui.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Si mette nei guai con una telefonata ad una hotline sexy. La sua carta di credito, dove vive, quanto guadagna, tutto gli riescono a carpire ‘sti delinquenti. Che sono capitanati dal (sempre bravissimo) Philip Seymour Hoffmann (quello di Magnolia e Capote).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Si innamora della tipa di prima, quella a cui aveva detto di no.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I delinquenti le fanno del male e lui s’incazza. Finalmente una valvola di sfogo appropriata per il nostro schizzatissimo Adam Sandler.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, il film finisce bene. C’e’ un lieto fine. Ci sono loro due che si vogliono bene. I cattivi sconfitti. Classica americanata, dirai tu ?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E invece no. Perche’ lui (Adam Sandler, lo schizzato) e’ bravissimo. Perche’ i dialoghi sono anticonvenzionali. Perche’ ci sono tre o quattro scene da vedere e rivedere come fossero belle fotografie (ad esempio: l’inizio del film, con il camioncino che si ribalta e perde l’oggetto misterioso con un schianto che rompe la l’alba di una &lt;span class="caps"&gt;L.A.&lt;/span&gt; periferica; la distruzione della vetrata nella casa della sorella; la violenza nel bagno del ristorante). &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="movies"></category></entry><entry><title>spanglish minireview</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2005-09-02-spanglish-minireview.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2005-09-02T09:55:00+02:00</published><updated>2005-09-02T09:55:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2005-09-02:/2005-09-02-spanglish-minireview.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;C’e’ una messicana bona dal cuore d’oro e con figlia a carico che si trasferisce a Los Angeles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Va a lavorare come sguattera nella villa di questi superamericani con la famiglia cosi’ composta:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;moglie (bionda) schizzata e puttana dalla lacrima facile;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;suocera mbriacona dalla lacrima facile;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;figlia sovrappeso e sensibile dalla lacrima facile;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;marito cuoco da 5 stelle …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;C’e’ una messicana bona dal cuore d’oro e con figlia a carico che si trasferisce a Los Angeles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Va a lavorare come sguattera nella villa di questi superamericani con la famiglia cosi’ composta:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;moglie (bionda) schizzata e puttana dalla lacrima facile;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;suocera mbriacona dalla lacrima facile;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;figlia sovrappeso e sensibile dalla lacrima facile;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;marito cuoco da 5 stelle dal cuore d’oro e (c’e’ bisogno di dirlo ?) dalla lacrima facile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La messicana impara l’inglese.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sua figlia vuole fare l’americana.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La moglie schizzata si vuole appropriare della vita della figlia della messicana.&lt;br/&gt;
Lui s’innamora di lei (della messicana); ovvio, essendo entrambi dal cuore d’oro sono fatti l’uno per l’altro.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finisce che i due riescono finalmente a trovarsi una notte insieme ma invece di trombare come ricci che fanno ? Parlano per tutta la notte. E poi lei scappa prima che sia troppo tardi. Mah.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finale edificante con la figlia della messicana orgogliosa della sua messicanita’.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Molte battute sono divertenti e Adam Sandler e’ parecchio bravo, ma mi aspettavo di piu’ dopo aver letto la recensione su &lt;a href="http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20041216/REVIEWS/41201005/1023"&gt;rogerebert.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="movies"></category></entry></feed>