<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>aadm - tv</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://aadm.github.io/feeds/tv.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://aadm.github.io/</id><updated>2010-06-16T00:26:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>lost hopes</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2010-06-16-lost-hopes.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-06-16T00:26:00+02:00</published><updated>2010-06-16T00:26:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2010-06-16:/2010-06-16-lost-hopes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The creators of Lost, in an interview given in 2005 (right after the
conclusion of season&amp;nbsp;1):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The survivors will not learn they are part of some dastardly experiment, or discover they are in purgatory, or wake up from a bad&amp;nbsp;dream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/18/arts/television/18manl.html"&gt;The Laws of the Jungle&lt;/a&gt; by Lorne Manly, 18 September&amp;nbsp;2005).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how did it end season 6 …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The creators of Lost, in an interview given in 2005 (right after the
conclusion of season&amp;nbsp;1):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The survivors will not learn they are part of some dastardly experiment, or discover they are in purgatory, or wake up from a bad&amp;nbsp;dream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/18/arts/television/18manl.html"&gt;The Laws of the Jungle&lt;/a&gt; by Lorne Manly, 18 September&amp;nbsp;2005).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how did it end season 6, exactly&amp;nbsp;?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="tv"></category></entry><entry><title>twentyfour</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2010-06-15-twentyfour.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-06-15T22:02:00+02:00</published><updated>2010-06-15T22:02:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2010-06-15:/2010-06-15-twentyfour.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been a &lt;a href="http://aadm.github.io/2007-02-13-24-talk.html"&gt;great fan of 24&lt;/a&gt; since its first season, years ago. I&amp;#8217;ve thoroughly enjoyed the first season, and also the second and the third. However, the show has been moving towards full improbability with the latest seasons. I think I also watched season 4, and then I don&amp;#8217;t remember anymore; maybe I&amp;#8217;ve also seen …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been a &lt;a href="http://aadm.github.io/2007-02-13-24-talk.html"&gt;great fan of 24&lt;/a&gt; since its first season, years ago. I&amp;#8217;ve thoroughly enjoyed the first season, and also the second and the third. However, the show has been moving towards full improbability with the latest seasons. I think I also watched season 4, and then I don&amp;#8217;t remember anymore; maybe I&amp;#8217;ve also seen season 5, but maybe I slept through some of the episodes &amp;#8212; I honestly don&amp;#8217;t recall. And then I didn&amp;#8217;t even know they made yet another season (number six), and now I can&amp;#8217;t be bothered finding out more about it even less watch&amp;nbsp;it.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suppose that&amp;#8217;s very bad for a show that started out so well and got me gripped for all the 24 episodes of its first season; I do remember long nights watching six or seven episodes one after the&amp;nbsp;other.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then something broke. These twenty-four episodes began to seem like a drag: and I actually fell asleep while Jack tortured yet another terrorist. Compare to the Sopranos or Dexter; twelve episodes for seasons, characters that are interesting and evolve through all these seasons and when there&amp;#8217;s nothing else to say then stop it for chrissake (the Sopranos rule here; Dexter goes on its 4th season now, I hope it won&amp;#8217;t be&amp;nbsp;disappointing).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: I wrote this in August 2009, when season 7 was just announced. I also wrote: &amp;#8220;So here comes season 7; will there be a change in 24 ? Will it grip me once again ? I don&amp;#8217;t know, but for now I really enjoyed the debate about the use of torture in the series&amp;#8221;. And about this last point, there are two really good documentaries that are worth watching: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HBO&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;Abu Ghraib&amp;#8221; and Errol Morris&amp;#8217; &amp;#8220;Standard Operating&amp;nbsp;Procedure&amp;#8221;.&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.newyorker.com/reporting/2007/02/19/070219fa_fact_mayer"&gt;Whatever it takes&lt;/a&gt;, by Jane Mayer. The New Yorker, 19 February&amp;nbsp;2007.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/01/08/arts/television/08fox.html"&gt;New Era in Politics, New Focus for 24&lt;/a&gt;, by Edward Wyatt, 7 January&amp;nbsp;2009.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="movies"></category><category term="tv"></category></entry><entry><title>24-talk</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2007-02-13-24-talk.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2007-02-13T08:37:00+01:00</published><updated>2007-02-13T08:37:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2007-02-13:/2007-02-13-24-talk.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Situation&lt;/strong&gt;: you are in the train with no ticket. The ticket inspector asks for your ticket. You lower your voice, and&amp;nbsp;say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;My name is Jack Bauer, I am following a suicide bomber who&amp;#8217;s right now on this train. Walk away and don&amp;#8217;t look&amp;nbsp;back&amp;#8221;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Situation&lt;/strong&gt;: you need a car to do your shopping for the weekend. You …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Situation&lt;/strong&gt;: you are in the train with no ticket. The ticket inspector asks for your ticket. You lower your voice, and&amp;nbsp;say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;My name is Jack Bauer, I am following a suicide bomber who&amp;#8217;s right now on this train. Walk away and don&amp;#8217;t look&amp;nbsp;back&amp;#8221;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Situation&lt;/strong&gt;: you need a car to do your shopping for the weekend. You spot a guy entering his Corvette, so you punch him in the face and while he&amp;#8217;s down,&amp;nbsp;shout:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Stay down&amp;nbsp;!&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Situation&lt;/strong&gt;: you need to check if your son is going to school or not. You call &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CTU&lt;/span&gt;, and&amp;nbsp;ask:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Chloe, Give me satellite&amp;nbsp;coverage&amp;#8221;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Situation&lt;/strong&gt;: You are in a meeting to discuss some business strategies, but you fall asleep. You wake up and there&amp;#8217;s your boss asking your opinion on somebody. You&amp;nbsp;reply:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Sir, we have to find him. Right now, he&amp;#8217;s our only chance of finding ( Sahid / Ahmed / Nazir&amp;nbsp;)&amp;#8221;.&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Situation&lt;/strong&gt;: you wife has been mistaken for Abu Asham (an islamic terrorist) and therefore killed by &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FBI&lt;/span&gt; agents, so you swear to God you&amp;#8217;ll never ever work for the government again. Then the President calls you asking to help his kid since he can&amp;#8217;t find his dog Bernie anymore. And obviously you retaliate&amp;nbsp;immediately: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Yes, mr.&amp;nbsp;President&amp;#8221;.&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Situation&lt;/strong&gt;: you are tortured by chinese agents. Special forces agents come to rescue you, then they give you to russian terrorists because if they don&amp;#8217;t these terrorists will detonate a nuclear device in Santa Barbara. The President calls you to say how sorry he is and that your sacrifice will not be in vain. You&amp;nbsp;say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Thank you, mr.&amp;nbsp;President&amp;#8221;.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="tv"></category></entry><entry><title>tv shows 2</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2005-11-04-tv-shows-2.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2005-11-04T18:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2005-11-04T18:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2005-11-04:/2005-11-04-tv-shows-2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been stuck at home due to a &lt;del&gt;minor&lt;/del&gt; major incident in the past 4 weeks, so I had the chance to enjoy a couple of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; series: Seinfeld (1st and 2nd season) and&amp;nbsp;Huff.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Seinfeld&lt;/em&gt; is a wickedly funny show &amp;#8220;about nothing&amp;#8221; as the americans say; never heard of it here in Italy, and I suppose that it …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been stuck at home due to a &lt;del&gt;minor&lt;/del&gt; major incident in the past 4 weeks, so I had the chance to enjoy a couple of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; series: Seinfeld (1st and 2nd season) and&amp;nbsp;Huff.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Seinfeld&lt;/em&gt; is a wickedly funny show &amp;#8220;about nothing&amp;#8221; as the americans say; never heard of it here in Italy, and I suppose that it&amp;#8217;s a kind of show that would not translate as well to the italian taste as Friends. So there&amp;#8217;s Jerry Seinfeld (a real first class stand-up comedian), his ex-grilfriend and two other buddies, New York and a local cafe&amp;#8217;, nice intermezzos where Seinfeld plays himself doing the stand-up comedy thing, and lots of brilliant jokes and comedy setups that you really love to watch&amp;#8217;em again and again.&lt;br&gt;
Mind you, it&amp;#8217;s really addictive stuff: once you begin watching it you will not stop. Believe&amp;nbsp;me.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Huff&lt;/em&gt; is a serious one. I like it because it&amp;#8217;s really got an adult, un-adulterated content. Harsh at times and sometimes dark as the Sopranos. A brilliant cast with that favourite of mine, Hank Azaria (some of you might remember him in Friends, playing Phoebe&amp;#8217;s geek scientist fiancee&amp;#8217;). Sometimes a little bit too sugary. Thanks god there&amp;#8217;s Russell Tupper, a cocaine-fueled sharp-mouthed lawyer that I&amp;#8217;ve just elected my personal hero of the&amp;nbsp;month. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="tv"></category></entry><entry><title>tv shows 1</title><link href="http://aadm.github.io/2005-08-24-tv-shows-1.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2005-08-24T06:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2005-08-24T06:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Alessandro Amato del Monte</name></author><id>tag:aadm.github.io,2005-08-24:/2005-08-24-tv-shows-1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t watch too much&amp;nbsp;tv.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My beatiful &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LCD&lt;/span&gt; widescreen &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; has a quiet life with me; not too much zapping (surely a source of stress not only for the zapper -me-, but also for the zapped -the tv-). Every once in a while, when I&amp;#8217;m stuck at home during the weekends (a rare event), I watch MotoGP …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t watch too much&amp;nbsp;tv.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My beatiful &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LCD&lt;/span&gt; widescreen &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; has a quiet life with me; not too much zapping (surely a source of stress not only for the zapper -me-, but also for the zapped -the tv-). Every once in a while, when I&amp;#8217;m stuck at home during the weekends (a rare event), I watch MotoGP or Superbike races. News, and what goes on in the world? I prefer the internet or the good old radio. Anyway I never dig too much in those subjects. It was different when I was living in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt;, I must say; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BBC&lt;/span&gt; news was at first a great way to learn spoken english (then I realized also the true meaning of unbiased news, a luxury that we don&amp;#8217;t have here in&amp;nbsp;Italy).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I&amp;#8217;m digressing. The point is that, even if I don&amp;#8217;t like &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt;, I love good &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; shows. I love them for the same reason I love long, lengthy books such as The Stand or Crime &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Punishment. I love them because I fall in love with the characters, and I like to see them and follow their lives for more than two&amp;nbsp;hours.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first show has been Friends; then I got to know Sopranos, this time after Daniele&amp;#8217;s recommendation. And then other shows, but I&amp;#8217;d like now to spend a few more words on these two&amp;nbsp;shows.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Friends&lt;/em&gt; is light; incredibly funny, I can watch any episode over and over again, and still have fun and laugh or at least smile. True, the characters don&amp;#8217;t evolve much; but I take it as feeling-good pill, just to laugh and smile and sometimes even cry (well, close to&amp;nbsp;it).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sopranos&lt;/em&gt; is dark; I love the guys, I love the dark humour, I love the way it&amp;#8217;s beatifully crafted and directed, almost as much as a full-feature movie, and more importantly I&amp;#8217;m deeply in love with the characters; Paulie, Chrissie, Sil, Adriana, Meadow, not to mention Tony of&amp;nbsp;course. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="tv"></category></entry></feed>